<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A handfull of holesome (though homelie) hearbs gathered out of the goodlie garden of Gods most holie word; for the common benefit and comfortable exercise of all such as are deuoutlie disposed. Collected and dedicated to all religious ladies, gentlewomen, and others; by Anne Wheathill, Gentlewoman.</title>
            <author>Wheathill, Anne.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 151 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842022</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 719:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A handfull of holesome (though homelie) hearbs gathered out of the goodlie garden of Gods most holie word; for the common benefit and comfortable exercise of all such as are deuoutlie disposed. Collected and dedicated to all religious ladies, gentlewomen, and others; by Anne Wheathill, Gentlewoman.</title>
                  <author>Wheathill, Anne.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 144 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By H[enrie] Denham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer-books --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:1"/>
            <p>A handfull of hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome (though homelie) hearbs, gathered out of the goodlie garden of Gods moſt holie word; for the common benefit and comfortable exerciſe of all ſuch as are deuoutlie diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>Collected and Dedicated to all religious Ladies, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, and others; by Anne Wheathill, Gentlewoman.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by H. Denham. 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:2"/>
            <head>To all Ladies, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, and others, which loue true religion and vertue, and be deuoutlie diſpoſed; Grace mercie, and peace, in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or a teſtimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to the world, how I haue and doo (I praiſe God) beſtowe the pretious treaſure of time, euen now in the ſtate of my virginitie or maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; lo heare I dedicate to all good Ladies, Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and others, who haue a deſire to inuocate and call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the Lord, a
<pb facs="tcp:6645:3"/> ſmall handfull of groſe hearbs; which I haue preſumed to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the garden of Gods moſt holie word. Not that there is anie vnpurenes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but that (peraduenture) my rudenes may be found to haue plucked them vp vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and without zeale.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon of the learned I may be iudged groſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; in preſuming, without the counſell or helpe of anie, to take ſuch an enterpriſe in hand: neuertheles, as GOD dooth know, I haue doone it with a good zeale, according to the weakenes of my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and capacitie. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be not ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in taſte, as they can find
<pb facs="tcp:6645:3"/> out, to whom God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſpirit of learning: yet doo I truſt, this ſmall handfull of groſe hearbs, holeſome in operation and workeing, ſhall be no leſſe acceptable before the maieſtie of almightie God than the fragrant floures of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, gathered with more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
            <p>But without preſumption I may boldlie ſaie, they haue not ſought them with a more willing hart and feruent mind; nor more to the aduancement of Gods glorie, &amp; the deſire of acceptation, than I haue doon. Which if I may obtaine, with the good iudgement and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of all my brethren and ſiſters in the Lord, I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:6645:4"/> thinke my time moſt happilie beſtowed: for that thereby I did auoid idlenes, to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of almightie God; and haue gained thoſe, whom I know not, as well ſtrangers to me, as my acquaintance, to be my freends, that ſhall taſte theſe groſe hearbs with me.</p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who moiſteneth all his elect with his moſt pretious blood, giue vs all a ſweete taſte in him: whome I humblie beſeech, from the bottome of my hart, to giue vnto thoſe that are vertuouſlie bent, a deſire to increaſe therein; and thoſe, which haue not yet reached therevnto, I praie the holie Ghoſt to inſpire their hearts
<pb facs="tcp:6645:4"/> from aboue, that they and we may be worthie to meete to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in the bleſſed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our heauenlie father, which his deare ſonne our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior Ieſus Chriſt did purchaſe for vs; whoſe bleſſed name, with the liuing father, and the holie Ghoſt, be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and magnified now and for euer, Amen, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in Chriſt,</hi> Anne Wheathill, <hi>Gent.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:5"/>
            <head>A table of the praiers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this booke, as they begin and followe one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in number; from 1. to 49.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Praier for the morning. praier. 1.</item>
               <item>A praier for remiſſion of ſins, &amp;c. praier. 2.</item>
               <item>An other praier for the ſame. 3</item>
               <item>An Euening praier. prai. 4.</item>
               <item>Againſt the temptation of the diuell, &amp;c. praier. 5.</item>
               <item>A praier for faith, and for Gods helpe and aſſiſtance, &amp;c. 6.</item>
               <item>Another for the ſame. prai. 7.</item>
               <item>A praier of the iuſtice of God, and of his mercie. prai. 8.</item>
               <item>A praier for humilitie, and a confeſſion of ſinnes, &amp;c. 9.</item>
               <item>A praier for patience in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:5"/> &amp;c. praier. 10.</item>
               <item>A praier wherein the bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of God is confeſſed and praiſed. praier. 11.</item>
               <item>A praier for grace and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. praier. 12.</item>
               <item>A praier wherein we deſire the life to come. praier. 13.</item>
               <item>A praier for comfort in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. praier. 14.</item>
               <item>A praier for the proſperitie of the church. praier. 15.</item>
               <item>A praier that we may be heard of God. praier. 16.</item>
               <item>A praier againſt the enimies of the church. praier. 17.</item>
               <item>A praier of the afflicted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. praier. 18.</item>
               <item>A praier of the iuſtice of God, &amp;c. praier. 19.</item>
               <item>A praier for faith &amp; grace. 20.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:6"/>
               <item>A praier of the creation of mankind, &amp;c. praier. 21.</item>
               <item>A praier &amp; thankſgiuing vnto God, for his manifold gifts, &amp;c. praier. 22.</item>
               <item>A praier wherin the hart pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth out it ſelfe before God, &amp;c. praier. 23.</item>
               <item>A praier wherein the afflicted perſon praieth againſt his enimies, &amp;c. praier. 24.</item>
               <item>A praier for the increaſe of faith, &amp;c. praier. 25.</item>
               <item>A praier vnto God the father, &amp;c. praier. 26.</item>
               <item>A praier vnto the ſonne of God, &amp;c. praier. 27.</item>
               <item>Another to the ſonne, &amp;c. 28.</item>
               <item>A praier vnto the holie Ghoſt, &amp;c. praier. 29.</item>
               <item>A praier in the remembrance
<pb facs="tcp:6645:6"/> of death, &amp;c. praier. 30.</item>
               <item>A praier to heare the word of God &amp; keepe it, praier. 31.</item>
               <item>A praier wherein the word of God is praiſed, &amp;c. pr. 32.</item>
               <item>A praier to be ſaid at all times, &amp;c. praier. 33.</item>
               <item>An humble confeſſion of our ſinnes before God, &amp;c. 34.</item>
               <item>A thankſgiuing vnto God for the redemption of the world, &amp;c. praier. 35.</item>
               <item>An other praier of praiſe and thankeſgiuing, &amp;c. 36.</item>
               <item>A breefe confeſſion, &amp;c. 37.</item>
               <item>A praier, ſhewing that none, but God, is omnipotent. 38.</item>
               <item>A praier of lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. 39.</item>
               <item>A praier, wherein the fatherlie loue and preſeruation of God is ſet foorth, &amp;c. 40.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:7"/>
               <item>A praier, for grace, &amp;c. 41.</item>
               <item>A praier againſt offenſes. 42.</item>
               <item>A praier for the good eſtate of the church, &amp;c. praier. 43.</item>
               <item>A praier, that the wiſdome of God is to be praiſed, &amp;c. 44.</item>
               <item>A praier wherein is ſhewed, how bleſſed they are that truſt in God, &amp;c. prai. 45.</item>
               <item>A praier of Gods maieſtie, 46.</item>
               <item>A praier, wherein is ſhewed how bleſſed they are that feare the Lord. praier. 47.</item>
               <item>A praier, ſhewing that God dwelleth in the harts of the righteous, &amp;c. 48.</item>
               <item>A praier, ſhewing that God is alwaies our protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. 49.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6645:7"/>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>1. A praier for the Morning.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Mightie maker &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of all things, God omnipotent, which like a diligent watchman, alwaies attendeſt vpon thy faithfull people, ſo that whether they ſléepe or wake, liue or die, thy prouidence neuer forſaketh them: looke fauourablie vpon me, O Lord, thy poore and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant, which am not woorthie, but through thy great mercies offered to me in Chriſt, once to lift vp mine
<pb facs="tcp:6645:8"/> eies vnto thy mercie ſeat.</p>
               <p>Wherefore in the name of thy déere ſonne my Lord and Sauiour, I offer vnto thée, through him, the ſacrifice of praiſe and thanks giuing; that thou haſt preſerued me both this night, and all the time and daies of my life hitherto, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this preſent houre. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée of thy great mercie to illuminate my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that I may lead and frame my life as thou haſt taught me in thy holie word, that my light may ſo ſhine here on earth, that my heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie father may be glorified in me, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and redéemer; for whoſe ſake heare me deare father,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6645:8"/> and ſend thy holie Ghoſt to direct me in all my dooings. To thée O glorious and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinitie, the Father, the Sonne, and the holie Ghoſt, be giuen all honor and praiſe, now and for euer more, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>2. A praier for remiſſion of ſinnes, for victorie againſt ſatan, and for the inward light of the ſoule.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Mercifull Father that art the ſure ſafegard and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of all that earneſtlie truſt in thée, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt not the death of ſinners, but their conuerſion and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life; I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:6645:9"/> vnto thy highneſſe, all mine offenſes by me commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which if I would hide from thée Lord, I could not. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the miſerable eſtate, whereto through ſinne I am brought: for thereby I haue worthilie loſt thy fauour, and am fallen from thy grace, which while thou withdraweſt from me, I can doo no good thing, nor thinke one good thought. My ſinnes haue cauſed thée to put me out of thy remembrance, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me, delaieng to giue me that which is my ſtrength and comfort. But how long wilt thou forget me, Lord? For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? How long wilt thou withdraw thy grace from me?</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6645:9"/>
               <p>Thou knoweſt my hartie contrition and ſorrowe; for that I haue vnkindlie forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thy ſeruice, and ſerued thine enimies, the diuell and ſinne. But truſting aſſuredlie in thy promiſe made to me, and all people, by the mouth of thy prophet Ezechiel, that is; If the ſinner will turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie from all his ſinnes, that he hath committed, and kéepe all thy commaundements, doubtles he ſhall liue and not die: as for all his ſinnes that he did before, thou wilt not thinke vpon them. I now moſt entirelie beſéech thée, that as my ſinnes were the cauſe, why thou diddeſt put me out of thy fauour; ſo let my hartie repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:6645:10"/> for them, cauſe thée to put my ſinnes out of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
               <p>Suffer me not long to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in this perplexitie of mind, and to take ſorrow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie in my hart from daie to daie, continuallie fearing the puniſhment due to my ſinne, and looking ſtill for thy comming into my ſoule by grace to deliuer me. Hope hath cauſed me long to looke for thée, that art my life and my health; thy long delaie in comming hath much increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my deſire; my feruent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire at length is now turned to a vehement paine. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make haſt Lord, I beſéech thée, to helpe my ſicke ſoule,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6645:10"/> and tarrie not.</p>
               <p>Let not mine enimie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell long triumph ouer me, whoſe propertie is to tread vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his féet, like a cruell prince, all thoſe that be vanquiſhed, euen to the pit of hell. He did long hold in captiuitie all mankind, vntill the comming and paſſion of Chriſt for our redemption; and ſince, through his craftie traines, he hath brought to vtter confuſion manie of thoſe that profeſſe thy ſonnes religion. Wherfore behold Lord, and conſider my miſerable eſtate, heare my humble petition, touching my deliuerance from out of his danger.</p>
               <p>Lighten the eie of my hart
<pb facs="tcp:6645:11"/> and vnderſtanding, with the light of thy grace and comfort, thereby expelling the darknes of ignorance. Lighten alſo one other eie of my ſoule, which is the eie of the affection. The ſight of this eie is ſo dimme, that it hath no perfect and true iudgement; yea it is ſo blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the vanities of this world, that one thing in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſéemeth to be twentie; like the ſight of the deceitfull eies of glaſſe. I beſéech thée ſaue my ſaid eie, that it be not put out by our enimie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell; and ſend me the light of grace, while I haue here time, &amp; ſpace of repentance, that at my latter end, mine enimies ſaie not with ioie, that they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6645:11"/> haue the vpper hand ouer me.</p>
               <p>But all my truſt is in thy mercie: for though thou hide thy ſelfe in a cloud, that my praier ſhould not go through it vnto thine eares; yet are not thy mercies cleane gone, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dooth thy louing kindnes ceaſe. Thou art therefore Lord my portion, and in thy mercie ſtill will I hope, and in none other creature; knowing for certaintie, that as God thou onelie maiſt helpe me, and as my louing father thou wilt helpe. Wherefore in thée my hart ſhall be ioifull, and in thy ſauing health, which is thy ſonne Chriſt our Sauiour and redéemer.</p>
               <p>The Philiſtines, knowing
<pb facs="tcp:6645:12"/> the preſence of thine arke to be in the campe of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits, on the daie of their battell, were ſore afraid, ſaieng; Who ſhall deliuer vs out of the hand of this mightie God? Much more will I be glad, and take ſure truſt, hauing the preſence and comfort of thy liuelie grace. And in token of the victorie which thou haſt giuen me ouer mine enimies, I will not ceaſe (as I haue good cauſe) to ſing the praiſes of the Lord, that hath ſo louinglie dealt with me, and magnifie the name of the moſt high, all the daies of my life, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:6645:12"/>
               <head>3. An other praier for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God giue me the excellent féeling of thine aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercie, for thou art my whole goodnes. Who am I, that I dare be ſo bold to ſpeake vnto thée? I am thy moſt poore ſinfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, a vile worme, and much more poore and miſerable, than I either know my ſelfe, or dare tell vnto thée: for my ſinnes ſticke ſo faſt to me, that I haue nothing, nor worthie anie thing. Thou onelie art good, thou iuſt, thou holie, and able to doo all things, and dooſt
<pb facs="tcp:6645:13"/> performe all things. Thou ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleſt all things, leauing the ſinfull onelie void and emptie.</p>
               <p>My conſcience accuſeth me ſo, that I can haue no reſt, till I be reconciled vnto thée O God my ſauiour. Remember thy mercies, O Lord, and fill my ſoule with thy fauour: for how may I continue in this life, vnleſſe thy mercie and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour doo ſtrengthen me? Giue me grace to put my whole truſt in thée, without grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or doubting: for I haue, and doo dailie waite for thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health.</p>
               <p>Turne not awaie thy face from me, neither withdraw thy comforts from me, leaſt my ſoule doo ſéeme in thy ſight
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6645:13"/> like vnto the earth that is void of moiſture. Lord teach me to doo thy will, learne me to walke worthilie and humblie before thée: for thou art my wiſedome, and knoweſt me what I am in all reſpects, and vnderſtandeſt my thoughts long before.</p>
               <p>Grant me alwaies to ſéeke thée in ſinglenes of heart: for the remembrance of thy fauor is more ſwéete vnto me, than all the pleaſures and deinties of the world. For my chéefeſt comfort is in thée O Chriſt, and not in anie worldlie meanes, who haſt ſaid; Who ſo ouercommeth the world, to them will I grant to féed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the trée of life. Which grant
<pb facs="tcp:6645:14"/> me for thy holie name ſake, to whom with the father, and the holie Ghoſt, be praiſe now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>4. An Euening praier.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Euerlaſting light, whoſe brightneſſe is neuer darkned; looke fauourablie vpon me thy poore and ſinfull ſeruant, who hath not onelie this daie, but all the daies and times of my life hitherto, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this preſent houre, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thy diuine Maieſtie, in thought, word, and déed; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I haue moſt iuſtlie prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thy wrath and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt me. And now I how the knées of my hart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6645:14"/> thée moſt mercifull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father, beſéeching thée for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to forgiue me all my ſinnes, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences and ignorances. For I confeſſe how wickedlie I haue miſpent the talent that thou gaueſt me, abuſing thy gifts of grace manie waies, burieng the ſame in obſcure darkneſſe, woorſe than the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant that hid his maiſters treaſure, not putting it to anie increaſe; for he deliuered the principall againe.</p>
               <p>But I moſt miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can ſhew vnto thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie no part of that which thou gaueſt me, to vſe to thine honor and glorie: for the which I am moſt hartilie ſorie, and
<pb facs="tcp:6645:15"/> doo vnfeinedlie repent, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no meane to helpe my ſelfe, but onelie to lift vp the eies of my faith vnto thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, beſéeching him moſt inſtantlie to make perfect my wants, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue whatſoeuer is lacking in me. For I commit my bodie and ſoule, this night and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, into his moſt holie hands; hoping, O Chriſt, thou wilt make me an acceptable ſacrifice vnto thy father.</p>
               <p>I haue no place to flie vnto, but to ſhrowd me vnder the wings of thine almightie power, who waſt ſo louing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that thou waſt conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſhed thy moſt pretious bloud, for the ſinnes of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6645:15"/> whole world; for the which I moſt humblie and hartilie yéeld vnto thée thanks, honor, praiſe and glorie.</p>
               <p>O lambe of God, ſonne of the father, heare thou me, thou that ſaiedſt; I am thy health and ſaluation, I am thy peace and life; cleaue faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and thou ſhalt liue. O Lord I am the woonded man, and thou art the good Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane: powre oile into my wounds, and bind them vp. Lord heale thou me, and I ſhall be whole: for thou art my God and Sauiour.</p>
               <p>Heare thou therefore my ſupplications from heauen, and haue mercie. Take from me all my ſinnes and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:16"/> and giue me thy grace and holie ſpirit. Lighten mine eies, that I ſléepe not in death: ſo ſhall I ioiefullie, after this ſluggiſh ſléepe of ſinne, riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, liuing in thy feare all the daies of my life. Which grant me to doo, O Father, Sonne, and holie Ghoſt, thrée perſons and one true GOD, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <head>5. Againſt the temptation of the diuell, and for Gods fauour and grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord preſerue me, that I fall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let me be as one of them that contemne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6645:16"/> thy word, falling from thée; but arme me with an inuincible ſtrength and conſtancie: ſo ſhall I be ſure, that all the powers of the world ſhall not ouercome me. For there is none in heauen, earth or hell, that can doo anie thing, but as thou giueſt them power. Sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all are thy creatures, thou muſt néeds gouerne and guide them.</p>
               <p>Thy mercie O God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is alſo annexed to thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, for when all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind was loſt and dead in ſinne, then diddeſt thou, ſitting in thy celeſtiall throne, looke downe to the earth vpon our miſerable ſtate, and looſedſt vs from the bands of the diuell,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:17"/> and ſendedſt downe thine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie begotten ſonne, that by his death he might deliuer from death, ſuch as worthilie were the children of death: for the which I praiſe thée, and doo confeſſe from the bottome of my hart, that our deliuerance commeth onlie of thée O God, and not by mans power.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I will not come emptie into thy preſence, but with all humilitie I offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée my troubled ſpirit for mine offenſes: and this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice I am ſure thou wilt not deſpiſe; for I confeſſe my ſelfe ignorant, till thou haſt taught me, O Lord. My heart is alſo variable, and ſeparated from thée. Ioine my ſoule and bodie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6645:17"/> to thée O God, and confirme me in thine obedience: for I deſire not to liue, but to ſerue thée as I ought, which we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doo aright, except thou o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our eies. I reſpect no man, but ſet thée alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, as the chéefe helper and iudge of my dooings.</p>
               <p>Certeinlie we can doo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our ſelues: but when thou O God dooſt inwardlie inſtruct vs by thy holie ſpirit, then féele we thy graces ſwée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the honie and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie combe. There is no accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perſons with thée, but all people that feare thée, and worke righteouſneſſe, thou wilt accept. If we be thine, thou Lord wilt ſtrengthen vs
<pb facs="tcp:6645:18"/> with all power, and bleſſe vs with all felicitie. But thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignations are moſt conſtant againſt the wicked, and paſſe all our vnderſtanding: for thou O God neuer forſakeſt anie that ſéeke vnto thée. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man is cauſe of his owne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Giue me thy fauour, and be mercifull vnto me for thine owne ſake: grant me thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie wiſedome and grace to be gouerned by thy holie word, which if I follow, I ſhall haue all proſperitie, corporall and ſpirituall, bringing foorth ſuch fruits as haue life. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that all my acts, thoughts, or anie part of my life cannot be hid from thée O
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6645:18"/> God, though thou ſéemeſt to be farre off; ſo that they are eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie knowne to thée: for thou O GOD vnderſtandeſt my meaning, before I ſpeake; and ſendeſt the dewes of thy grace vpon me, which cauſeth me to bring foorth the fruits of good works, to thine honour, and the helpe of my neighbor: for it is of thy power, ſtrength, and grace, when I doo anie thing that is good, and not of mine owne power.</p>
               <p>There is none good, but thou alone; thou killeſt and giueſt life; thou woundeſt, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt whole: neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that can ſpeake a word, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou giue it him, nor none can ſaue himſelfe by his owne
<pb facs="tcp:6645:19"/> labour, nor anie worldlie meanes. Wherfore I will reſt in thée, as mine onelie God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>6. A praier for faith, and for Gods helpe and aſſiſtance at his good pleaſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord GOD al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, which by thy power &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome haſt made all the world, and dooeſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the ſame, and all that therein is: from thy holie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, wherein thou dwelleſt, looke fauorablie vpon vs, and grant that in temptation we may haue faith to fight againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6645:19"/> the diuell, and all his falſe ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, and to crie inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnto thée with groning, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies aiding vs with thy holie ſpirit, to be humble in all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, with true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For when all mans helpe dooth faile, thou O God wilt helpe vs, euen as it were by a miracle; if we call vpon thée with an vpright conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>Lord grant vs neuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more of thée, than is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie; neither to ſéeke to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate thy power from thy will, leaſt we ſhould tempt thée: for though thy helpe dooth not preſentlie appeare, yet haſt thou ſowen and laid vp in ſtore for vs. We will therefore be
<pb facs="tcp:6645:20"/> mindfull of thy benefits, and onelie truſt in thy defenſe: for though the wicked rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée O God, yet thoſe that be thy children ſhall praiſe thy name and mightie power. For the more liberallie that thou O God dooeſt deale with thy people, the more dooſt thou puniſh them that abuſe thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits. For thou O God haſt care ouer thine, and dooeſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten them for their health, that they ſhould not periſh for euer with the wicked. For thou wilt reſtore the gouernement of good things to their vſe, and then the godlie ſhall follow thée chéerefullie.</p>
               <p>Grant vs we humblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée to know thy waies,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6645:20"/> and to aſcend vp vnto the throne of thy maieſtie by faith, giuing thée praiſe and glorie, for thy fatherlie preſeruation and health towards vs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie. For thou haſt béene a houſe and defenſe for vs: thou haſt choſen vs to be thy people, before the foundation of the earth was laid. Wherefore we are ſure that thou wilt heare vs, whenſoeuer we call and crie vnto thée for mercie and grace. Bleſſe vs now and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with all goodnes, that we may lead our liues according to thy will, liuing in thy feare all the daies of our life, that after this courſe is ended, we may dwell with thée, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:21"/>
               <head>7. Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Make my humble petition in thy ſight, O GOD moſt holie, which biddeſt vs aſke, and it ſhall be giuen; ſéeke, and we ſhall find; knocke, and it ſhall be opened vnto vs; and beléeue onelie, and we ſhall receiue whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we deſire. Lord I beléeue, helpe thou mine vnbeléefe, and giue me that faith which ſhalbe moſt acceptable in thy ſight. Sowe in my heart, good Lord the graine of ſtedfaſt faith, which may aſpire and ſpring vp vnto the mercie ſeat of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6645:21"/> thine almightie maieſtie: for without true faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we cannot call vpon thée a right.</p>
               <p>Giue me therefore, good Lord, that moſt pretious iewel of faith, that thou maiſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by heare me. And giue me comfort &amp; ſaluation through thy mercifull goodneſſe, O God, who neuer dooeſt forſake thy faithfull ſeruants, that come to thée in humbleneſſe of heart, looking vpon Ieſus Chriſt thy deare ſonne our Lord and Sauiour: for he is the trée of life, which ſtandeth in the middeſt of paradiſe, by whom we haue entrance vnto thée O déere father.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer ſéeketh anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:6645:22"/> waie than this thy déere Sonne, he is a théefe and a robber, and ſhall neuer be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the benefits, which he of his mercie hath moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinglie beſtowed vpon vs: which grant me Lord Ieſu ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to forget, but euermore to ſhew my ſelfe thankefull. For it is thou O Lord that art worthie to receiue all glorie, honour, and praiſe: for thou haſt created and redéemed all, and without thée we cannot doo anie thing that is good.</p>
               <p>Wherefore Lord Ieſus I come vnto thée, crauing at thy mercifull hand an humble and contrite heart, a patient mind, a quiet conſcience, the gift of faith, and of the holie
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6645:22"/> Ghoſt. O thou louer of ſoules, heare me poore wretch, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though vnworthie once to thinke, much leſſe to ſpeake vnto thy maieſtie. But thou art the ſame Lord, who dooeſt moſt louinglie ſaie; Come to me all ye that are heauie lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will eaſe you.</p>
               <p>Which comfortable ſaieng of thine, O Chriſt, maketh me bold to come into thy preſence, vnloding my ſinfull ſacke of corruption, before the face of thine almightie power; not doubting but thou wilt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie heare me, and eaſe me with thy helpe: for I caſt all my burthen on thée, who art the giuer of life and ſaluation. Wherefore I turne my ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:6645:23"/> vnto thée O Lord Ieſus Chriſt deſiring thée by praier to renue whatſoeuer is amiſſe in me, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by mine owne frailtie, or malice of the diuell.</p>
               <p>For I acknowledge, O Lord, that I am the moſt wicked, the moſt fraile of all others, the weakeſt to reſiſt my ghoſtlie enimie. But I truſt, through thy mercie, to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, for whom thou haſt ouercome the diuell and the world: which grant me, Lord Ieſus, for thy bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſake, that after this life I may enioie the endles bliſſe and glorie of heauen. To thée, with the liuing Father, and the holie Ghoſt, be giuen all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, all praiſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6645:23"/> and thanks, for euer and euer, Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <head>8. A praier of the iuſtice of God, and of his mercie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, from whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be hid or kept ſecret, thou art the ſearcher of the hart and reines, which knoweſt the thoughts of all men: when I remember thy iuſt iudgment, I tremble and quake for feare, conſidering the burthen, wait, and filthines of ſinne to be ſo great, that for one proud thought, a great number of angels fell from heauen. The
<pb facs="tcp:6645:24"/> earth was not able to beare the burthen of Corah, Dathan and Abiram; but for the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt thée and thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant Moſes, the earth opened, and ſwallowed them quicke.</p>
               <p>For the ſinne and pride of Dauid, who muſtered his men, putting his truſt in the multitude of them, rather than in thée that art the liuing God, thou ſcourgedſt him with the plague of peſtilence, ſo that there died foure ſcore thouſand of his people, within the ſpace of thrée daies.</p>
               <p>Who would not then feare, ſéeing we ſinne dailie with moſt gréeuous ſinnes? Now haue we no remedie to flie from thy wrath, but to ſhrowd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6645:24"/> our ſelues in the boſome of thy moſt dearelie beloued ſonne, our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, making him our bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke and houſe of defenſe, betwéene thine anger and vs: moſt humblie beſéeching thée for his ſake, and for the bitter paines that he ſuffered for our redemption, to be mercifull vnto vs, and rebuke vs not in thine anger.</p>
               <p>Let not the ſentence of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death take place, which thou gaueſt againſt Adam, and all his poſteritie for his diſobedience. Thou art méeke, gentle, and long ſuffering of thy ſelfe. It is our gréeuous offenſes, heaped one vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that prouoke thée vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6645:25"/> anger. Therefore, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our offenſes, we praie thée moſt mercifull father, to haue compaſſion vpon vs: for we are not able of our ſelues to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe; it is thou Lord, and thy bleſſed ſonne that muſt heale our infirmities.</p>
               <p>We haue no ſtrength to withſtand the temptation of our enimies, thy ſonne Chriſt muſt reach vs his hand, as he did to <hi>Peter,</hi> walking on the water, when he was in perill of drowning. His patience is our medicine and health, thy grace and his are ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. We are all carnall, ſold vnder ſinne; ſo that the good we would doo, that doo we not; but the euill that we wold
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6645:25"/> not, that we doo. We are all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of our ſelues. Conſider O God our contrite hearts, and penitent minds, and heare, heale, and amend vs.</p>
               <p>Hope biddeth vs ſtill to crie and call vpon thée for helpe, as the woman, of Canaan cried ſtill vpon thy ſonne Chriſt for the helpe of hir daughter, and at the laſt was heard to hir owne contentation: ſo we, knocking and calling ſtill, doubt not but thou wilt grant, through our importunacie, our deſires, as he that gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his neighbour thrée loaues.</p>
               <p>We doo now knocke, crie, and will neuer ceaſe, till thou Lord turne towards vs, and deliuer our ſoules. Turne, we
<pb facs="tcp:6645:26"/> heartilie beſéech thée, from thy wrath, to pittie and mercie; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from the manifold troubles which we haue in our conſciences. Oh ſaue vs for thy mercie ſake, for thy bleſſed Sonne Ieſus hath dearelie bought vs. Wherefore Lord, we thy faithfull creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through thy grace, and the battell of thy ſonne vpon the croſſe reſtored to thy fauour; and hauing the houſe of our hearts and ſoules ſwept and made cleane from all vices, which were woont to inhabite in vs, we moſt humblie praie thée to giue vs ſtrength, to kéepe our ſoules from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion of the wilie ſerpent.</p>
               <p>Dwell in vs ſtill by thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6645:26"/> grace, make vs to be of thy houſhold, that we may liue and praiſe thée in this world, and after this life we may enioie the bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thine eternall maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, one God in perſons thrée, and euerlaſting in vnitie, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <head>9. A praier for humilitie, and a confeſſion of ſinnes, with a petition to haue the ſame remitted.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord giue me hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, being the beautifull flowre of vertue that gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the garden of mans ſoule; one of the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:27"/> moſt neceſſarie, and moſt acceptable, whoſe power was ſo great, that it drue the ſonne of GOD, the ſecond perſon in deitie, from heauen, into the wombe of the méeke virgine, whom of all other he choſe to be his mother, for that ſhe was ſo humble and vertuous. Thou O Chriſt our Sauiour, being Lord of all the world, walkedſt all the daies of thy life in humilitie, and therein endedſt, humbling thy ſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vile death of the croſſe.</p>
               <p>The wiſe humilitie of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gael</hi> pacified the furie of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> when he was minded to kill all the men of the houſe of hir huſband. The humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6645:27"/> the wrath of GOD, which was the cauſe that the almightie preſerued him all the daies of his life. The great goodnes of this vertue is made manifeſt, by opening the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſnes of the vice contrarie thereto, which is pride: which appeared in the proud Phariſie, when he made boaſt in his praiers of his good déeds, and deſpiſed his poore neighbour, which cauſed his praier not to be hard, when the poore Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, ſtanding a farre off, with humbleneſſe, durſt not lift vp his eies to heauen, but with heartie repentance knocking his breaſt, ſaid; Lord be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me a ſinner: which har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie confeſſion of his ſinne, was
<pb facs="tcp:6645:28"/> cauſe of his iuſtification, and that he was made righteous.</p>
               <p>Wherefore moſt gratious Lord our heauenlie father, conſidering the power of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and the knowledge of our ſinnes, with hartie repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to be of ſo great effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; I thy poore creature, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie to appeare before thy maieſtie, doo powre downe here, before thée, my ſacke that is full of ſinne, which I haue committed euen from my youth, they are great and manie, without number: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, truſting of thine accuſtomed nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, which is, to be mercifull to all ſinners, that be ſorie for their offenſes from the bottom
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6645:28"/> of their hearts, turning to thée, knowing that thou diddeſt ſend thy louing ſonne, not to call thoſe that ſéeme in their owne ſight to be iuſt, but to helpe thoſe that confeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ſinners.</p>
               <p>I therefore, Lord, willing by the helpe of thy grace, vtterlie to forſake ſinne, and to fulfill thy holie will hereafter, deſire thée humblie of forgiueneſſe, and to admit me among the number of thoſe that are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and their vnrighteouſnes forgiuen. I will not couer from thée my ſinnes, neither yet excuſe them; but I praie thée Lord hide them in the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die woonds of thy ſonne Chriſt, where they ſhall be put in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb facs="tcp:6645:29"/> obliuion. Bleſſed is the man, vnto whom thou dooſt not impute ſinne, and in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</p>
               <p>Wherfore from the bottome of my heart, Lord, I am ſorie for all my ſinnes, and doo aſke thée forgiueneſſe. I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge all mine offenſes, and accuſe my ſelfe vnto thée Lord. So ſoone as I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined no longer to hide mine euill waies, thou Lord ſtraite forgaueſt me. Thine eare was in my heart, before my voice was in my mouth. Thy mercies waſhed awaie my ſinnes, or euer my confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was made. Thou art as readie to heare and forgiue, as we to aſke.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6645:29"/>
               <p>Wherefore I will ſaie with the prophet <hi>Daniel;</hi> It is I that haue offended and ſinned againſt thy maieſtie. I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie beſéech thée cure my ſicke ſoule, for I haue highlie ſinned againſt thée; yet doubt I not, but thou haſt and wilt forgiue the wickednes of my ſinne. It is thou Lord that muſt helpe vs; which thou wilt doo, if we call vpon thée, whilſt we are in this life, for after death, no intreatie will be heard. It is then too late.</p>
               <p>Wherefore Lord kéepe vs in the right waie, and ſuffer vs not to ſwarue on the right hand, nor on the left. Thy eies of protection and mercie are euer firmelie fixed vpon vs;
<pb facs="tcp:6645:30"/> grant vs to ſet the eies of our minds vpon thée. Lord call me, plucke me Lord from mine vngodlines, that I may knowe thée, loue thée, &amp; put my hope wholie in thée. O glorious God, my maker, ſauiour, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier, dwell in me and giue me grace to dwell in thée, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="prayer">
               <head>10. A praier for patience in trouble, and constant expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Gods goodnes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD almightie, grant vs neuer to refuſe thy chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. For though thou make a wound, thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt a plaiſter; though thou ſmite, thy hand maketh whole againe. Thou ſhalt deliuer vs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6645:30"/> in ſixe troubles, and in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth there ſhall none euill come vnto vs. In hunger thou ſhalt ſaue vs from death; and when it is war, from the power of the ſword; thou ſhalt kéepe vs from the euill toong; and when trouble commeth, we ſhall not néed to feare. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and death we ſhall be merrie: for the ſtones of the land ſhall be confederate with vs, bicauſe the Lord of hoſts is our defenſe &amp; refuge for euer.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore put our whole truſt in him, reioiſing with melodie of thankſgiuing vnto his maieſtie, who onelie is true, and can helpe vs with deliuerance. Let vs lift vp our eies vnto GOD, who hath all
<pb facs="tcp:6645:31"/> power; and therefore ought to be feared. For whatſoeuer he be that feareth man, more than God, falleth into a ſnare, and is deſtroied. As for all our ſinnes and tranſgreſſions, thou requireſt nothing of vs, O Lord GOD, but to turne vnto thée, and to obeie thy holy word, following thy precepts and commandements.</p>
               <p>For thou ſaieſt, O Lord, thoſe that honour thée, thou wilt exalt; and whoſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth thée, ſhall be deſpiſed. For thou preferreſt to honour, and putteſt downe, according to thy bleſſed will. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked when they féele thy heauie hand, grudge at the ſame: but the godlie humble themſelues,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6645:31"/> and crie for mercie. For thou O Lord wilt not heare hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits, but thoſe that praie vnto thée with an vnfained faith, and true repentance. For the praier of the faithfull is a barre to ſtaie thine anger, that thou conſume not all.</p>
               <p>Thy mercie is ſo great to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thine, that thou wilt not deſtroie them for their ſinnes, but correct and chaſten them, till thou haue purged and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned them. Thy fauour O God is cauſe of all proſperitie, and thine anger of all aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For thy care is ſo much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thine, that thou wilt cauſe their verie enimies to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them. It lieth in thy mightie power, to gouerne
<pb facs="tcp:6645:32"/> the hearts of all, thou O God preferreſt and preſerueſt them, which are zealous of thy glorie, and haue a care and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their brethren: as for them that forget thée in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie, who art the giuer of all good things, they procure to themſelues vtter perdition. For thou doſt caſt them behind thy backe; but thy louing countenance dooth comfort the troubled, that patientlie wait on thée, conſtantlie putting their truſt in thy mercie.</p>
               <p>In this world is continuall trouble and diſquietnes: in heauen is perpetuall reſt. Yet manie there be, who loue this world, that could content themſelues, for lacke of faith,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6645:32"/> that are loth to looſe things certein for things vncertaine. But thy faithfull know, throgh faith, that when in this world the daie paſſeth awaie, then commeth the night &amp; darknes: but in heauen all is there but one daie eternall, a life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, which endureth for euer, which the ſoule of the righteous ſhall enioie, through thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies O GOD, bicauſe in this world they walked before thée; of which number make me one, for his ſake that died for me; to whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holie Ghoſt, be giuen all honour and praiſe, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:33"/>
               <head>11. A praier wherein the bountifulnes of God is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and praiſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God eternall, the giuer of all felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whoſe loue is like the euening and morning raine vpon the earth, whoſe mercies cannot be numbered, whoſe wiſdome and diuine prouidence is ſuch, that it reacheth from one end of the earth vnto an other: moſt mightilie and louinglie dooeſt thou order all things. Thy bountifulneſſe, Lord, to all mankind, is ſo manfeſt, that no reaſonable creature can ſaie, but that he hath taſted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6645:33"/> thereof: for what good thing hath man that he hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of thee?</p>
               <p>Thou art good to all men, but ſpeciallie to thoſe that haue an vpright conſcience, and ſtraight heart, a mind not bowing downe to carnall and temporall things, but aſpiring vnto heauenlie and eternall things: for it is not enough, O God almightie, to praiſe thée with mouth, except our whole hart agrée therevnto, framing our life vnto the ſame; for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer dooth otherwiſe than thou haſt commanded, dooth pollute thy name. Wherefore giue vs grace to feare thée, and to obeie thy holie word. Giue vs alſo a mind to praiſe
<pb facs="tcp:6645:34"/> thée for thy benefits paſt, that thereby our minds may be ſtrengthened againſt all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils. When I haue grace, O Lord, to take thée for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe &amp; truſt, I ſhall perceiue thy protection to be a moſt ſure ſafegard vnto me. For though I haue not altogither hither to known thy Maieſtie, as I ought to doo; yet I moſt humblie thanke thée Lord, that I went not from thée; but did cleaue faſt to thée by faith.</p>
               <p>Though I had almoſt ſlipped and fallen from thée, yet I did not forſake thée. And thou full mercifullie knowing my good will towards thée, didſt hold me vp by my right hand, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6645:34"/> thou didſt <hi>Peter,</hi> when he was in iopardie of drowning; thy goodneſſe brought me to the knowledge of mine infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, thy grace called me from mine error into the right waie, thou ſaueſt me as thou didſt <hi>Lot</hi> and his houſe, thou didſt lead me with thy counſel, preſeruing my weakeneſſe in this preſent life. Wherefore my truſt is, that thou wilt not take thy ſpirit from me, but wilt receiue me into glorie: for thy fauor hath béen my guide.</p>
               <p>Thy grace dooth direct me in all my dooings, by which I am that I am, and thy grace held me ſtill through faith. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my truſt is, that thou wilt not leaue me, but bring me to
<pb facs="tcp:6645:35"/> thine euerlaſting reſt. What wretched foole therefore was I, to deſire of thée, temporall, fraile, and deceitfull proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and pleaſure; knowing by faith, that thou haſt prepared for me, and for all faithfull that loue thée, ſuch rewards as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eie hath ſéene, eare hath heard, nor hart can imagine?</p>
               <p>What is ther then that is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for me? Euen thou thy ſelfe Lord, and the fruition of thy perfect Godhead, wherein is included all the ioie that may be deuiſed, a treaſure that is immortall, it indureth plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant for euer. Shall I then be ſo mad, to deſire of thée moſt mercifull God, worldlie ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, pleaſure, eaſe, or riches,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6645:35"/> more than is requiſite for this preſent life? Should I deſire of thée that loueſt me, thoſe gifts, wherewith thou rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thine enimies?</p>
               <p>The moſt wicked vpon the earth haue theſe trifles of thy great goodnes and liberalitie, but there is nothing vpon the earth that I deſire ſaue onelie thée. The ſwéetnes of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hath made all euill to ceaſe in me: for thou Lord art becom the ſtrength of my hart, thou art my portion for euer, thou art my reward thine owne ſelfe, wherwith my hart is ſufficed. For thou art the verie life it ſelfe, in whom who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beléeueth, ſhall liue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinglie, and ſhall not
<pb facs="tcp:6645:36"/> come into damnation.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it is good for me, to hold me faſt by thée, to draw néere vnto thée by faith, from whence good works doo ſpring towards my neighbour, and then to put my hope and truſt wholie in thée, as in a ſure and vnmooueable altar, from whence no blaſt of winds of temptation ſhall driue me. Through hope I truſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from a corruptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, into thy heauenlie glorie: and this by patience I now abide and looke for. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whileſt I liue, I will not ceaſe to declare and ſet foorth all thy noble works, which thou haſt wrought, to thine honor and praiſe, and to the profit of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6645:36"/> them that ſhall profeſſe the ſame Chriſts religion, while the world indureth. As for me, I haue none other refuge but thée, in whom my conſcience dooth reſt: for thou O God haſt humbled me by affliction, that I ſhould crie vnto thée, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the fruit of thy promiſe: which grant O father, ſonne, and holie ghoſt, to me and all thy church to aſpire vnto, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="prayer">
               <head>12. A praier for grace and repentance.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, we are aſhamed, &amp; dare not lift vp our eies vnto thée our
<pb facs="tcp:6645:37"/> God; for our wickedneſſe is gone ouer our head, and our treſpaſſes are waxen ſo great, that they reach vp vnto the heauens. Since the time of our fathers, we haue ſinned &amp; treſpaſſed againſt thée, euen vnto this daie: and now our God, what ſhall we ſaie? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie doo we forſake thy commandements, and harden our harts in miſbeléefe: but thou O God open our eies, to behold thée with a ſtedfaſt faith; &amp; the eares of our harts, to heare thy words, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, that we may know thée the onlie true God, and Ieſus Chriſt whome thou haſt ſent; for whoſe ſake heare vs, O déere Father, and ſend
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6645:37"/> thy holie Ghoſt, to confirme this faith in vs euermore. To whom, with thée O Father, &amp; thy ſon our onlie ſauiour, be all honor and glorie, power and dominion, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <head>13. A praier wherein wee deſire the life to come.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt high &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie prince of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, Lorde of hoſts, GOD and Lord of the heauenly armie of angels, that are thy miniſters: when I conſider the greatnes of thy mightie Maieſtie, I am ſo rapt with the deſire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that my hart and my fleſh
<pb facs="tcp:6645:38"/> reioiceth in nothing but in thée alone, that art the liuing God. All earthlie tabernacles and worldlie goods I nothing eſtéeme, when I behold thine euerlaſting felicitie, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I ſée now but darkelie as in a glaſſe; I hope to ſée thée face to face.</p>
               <p>Grant me therfore O Lord, whileſt I am in this taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, to build vpon faith, which is the altar of thée that art the Lord moſt mightie, my King and my God, vpon which we giue vnto thée ſacrifice, laud and praiſe in the vnitie of thy faithfull Church, whereof thy Sonne Chriſt is the ſure rock. The faithfull build on this foundation. Bleſſed are they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6645:38"/> Lord therefore, that dwell in thy houſe, who haue occaſion to praiſe thée. They are repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with aboundance of all things that they deſire, they are made like vnto thée, they ſée thée, euen as thou art; of which ſight they ſhall neuer be fullie ſatiſfied: ſuch ioie and loue ſhall they conceiue of the ſight of thy glorious maieſtie.</p>
               <p>But to this beatitude can we not atteine, mercifull God, of our owne ſtrength and power; but through the helpe of thy gratious aſſiſtance. Thou muſt ingraue in our harts thy lawes, and direct vs in thy waies; and when we are brought to thée by the right waie, we muſt be continuallie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:39"/> aided by thy grace, that thou maieſt ſtaie and kéepe our féet from ſlipping. Who ſo truſteth to his owne ſtrength or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or to the helpe of man, is much deceiued, and leaneth to a rotten ſtaffe: contrariwiſe, he that putteth his truſt in thy gratious power, wanteth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuccour at néed.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt put vs into this preſent world, to fight and to ſtriue with our enimies, who doo continuallie aſſault vs; but thy grace maketh vs able to repell all their inuaſions. Thou ſuffereſt vs not to be tempted aboue our ſtrength, and for our triumph thou rewardeſt vs with a crowne of glorie and immortalitie.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6645:39"/>
               <p>The vngodlie fall from thée, deſcending downeward from one vice to an other: but thy faithfull and elect increaſe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in godlines. For of thée Lord commeth all our power and ſtrength to doo good, and of thy ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, our maiſter, our teacher and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, who promiſeth, that if we wéepe and morne heare in this vale of miſerie for our ſinnes; we ſhall hereafter laugh and be ioifull in eternall glorie.</p>
               <p>If we ſowe with heauines, we ſhall reape with gladnes; if we perſeuere good &amp; ſtrong champions héere in batell, we ſhall for our reward behold thy glorious face, in thy heauenlie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:40"/> manſion; we ſhall ſée alſo thy ſonne Chriſt, who is thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thy power, which who ſo ſéeth, enioieth all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: to ſée that delectable ſight, our hearts doo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of thée, that art the Lord of hoſts.</p>
               <p>For this we make humble petition to thée, that art the GOD of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who wreſtled with thine angel, and preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; whoſe name thou diddeſt change, and calledſt him Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, that is, the feare or beholder of God. Euen ſo make me a ſtrong wreſtler againſt mine enimies in this world, that I may after this life behold thy incomprehenſible deitie, to the full contentation both of my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6645:40"/> ſoule and bodie.</p>
               <p>We are much vnworthie to obteine anie thing of thée, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering our vnkindnes ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto thée, and our wretched eſtate: wherein we remaine. Neuertheleſſe Lord, we praie thée to be our defender and protector, through thy grace; not for our merits, but for the merits of thy moſt entirelie beloued ſonne Chriſt, thine onelie annointed aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the oile of ioie and gladnes. He is our head, we are the members of his bodie: he dwelleth in his faithfull, and they in him. Who ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth anie of his elect, receiueth him. He was incarnate for vs, ſuffered death for vs, bare our
<pb facs="tcp:6645:41"/> iniquities on his backe, and roſe againe for our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we doubt not, but that through the infuſion of thy grace, thou wilt looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in vs, and ſhewe vs mercie for his ſake; that we may haue aboundance of grace through him, and caſting all the vanities of this world behind our backes, we may enter into the court of thy bright heauenlie Ieruſalem, where one daies abiding is better than a thouſand in this wretched world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> (as witneſſeth our Sauiour) was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt perfect vpon earth: yet (ſaid he) the leaſt in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6645:41"/> the kingdome of heauen is greater than he. Wherefore moſt mightie Lord, thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doubt not, whilſt they are here in this vale of miſerie, but that thou wilt euer aſſiſt them, guide them, and bleſſe them that put their whole truſt in thée, who art the liuing God, and giueſt to thine aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantlie all things neceſſarie to this preſent life; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the fruition of thy Godhead in heauen eternallie, there to dwell with thée euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:42"/>
               <head>14. A praier for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in trouble.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chiefeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that I receiue in this miſerable, wretched, &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome world, O heauenlie Father, and God almightie, is, when I call to mind the truth of thy great promiſes, made to me in Ieſus Chriſt, for whoſe ſake onelie I doo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe, that thou art my mercifull and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father, and ſo careſt for me through him, that nothing is able to remooue thy grace and fauour from me. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I come vnto thée in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of hart, crauing at thy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6645:42"/> bountifull hands the aſſiſtance of thy holie ſpirit, to ſuppreſſe my wicked affections, that I may with a ſtedfaſt faith obeie thy moſt diuine Maieſtie, in thought, word, and déed. For thou diſpoſeſt all things moſt wiſelie, and preſerueſt thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in their greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Wherefore thy holie name be praiſed now and for euermore, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="prayer">
               <head>15. A praier for the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie of the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt holie, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and bleſſed trinitie, thrée per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in one God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:43"/> by whoſe goodneſſe all creatures haue their being, whoſe eies behold althings, as well that are paſt, as that are to come, and are accoumpted as preſent to thy mightie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie: we thy poore faithful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the Church here mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant vpon earth, ſhew foorth our lamentable praiers, beſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thée pitifullie to behold the miſerable eſtate thereof, which neuer had more néed of thy godlie aſſiſtance than at this preſent it hath.</p>
               <p>The nature of man is ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and abhominable in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, that none dooth good vpon the earth; for many there be that deſpiſe God, &amp; oppreſſe the poore. Wherefore, Lord, we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6645:43"/> beſéech thée, to ariſe vp for the trouble ſake of the oppreſſed, and at the complaint of the poore, helpe him, and ſet him at reſt.</p>
               <p>Thy Sonne Chriſt is our ſauing health, in whom who ſo truſteth, reſteth in ſuertie, and cannot be deceiued. Ariſe vp we praie thée mercifull God, and caſt vs not away for euer; comfort thy ſmall flocke, to the confuſion of thine enimies; and make vs able, through thy grace, to kéepe thy lawes, which are pure; euen as the ſiluer, which from the earth is tried and purified ſeuen times in the fire.</p>
               <p>Thou art néere Lord vnto all, that in this life call vpon
<pb facs="tcp:6645:44"/> thée faithfullie; and thou kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt them from all dangers: for in the midſt of this world, we are in manie temptations and vices, and in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the proud and wicked people, and in manie tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. We ſée the vanities of this world readie to mooue vs, we ſuffer perſecution; yet thou kéepeſt vs from deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thy grace preſerueth vs, that they come not néere vs. Their entiſements we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme not, bicauſe we hope in thy mightie power, who art our defenſe in trouble.</p>
               <p>Thy ſonne Chriſt is the ſtrong rocke, in the which all birds that build doo reſt out of ieopardie; to him all ſinners
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6645:44"/> maie ſlie for ſuccour and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, being holden by him, they may be eaſed. This rocke the diuell cannot vndermine nor ſcale: no water of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can drowne thoſe that build on this rocke. <hi>Pharao</hi> king of Aegypt, with a great hoſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the children of Iſrael, but he could not hurt them: thou Lord waſt their defenſe, and diddeſt deſtroie all their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries. Euen ſo art thou our defenſe, our hope, and our comfort.</p>
               <p>Thou wilt compaſſe vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with ioifull deliuerance. The houſe of our bodies is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed with enimies, but thy prouidence will defend vs out of all dangers. Thou wilt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb facs="tcp:6645:45"/> vs, and ſhewe vs the waie wherin we ſhall go. This life is a pilgrimage, and a iorneie for vs to trauell in. Thou art the end of our waie, O God. Thou art the marke that we ſhoote at, when we come to our iornies end, in thée Lord we hope to haue reſt. Thou giueſt knowledge and inſtruction by faith, that if we paſſe well through this world, we ſhall haue ioie euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinglie: to the which bring vs all, thou Lord that diedſt for vs all, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="prayer">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6645:45"/>
               <head>16. A praier, that we may be heard of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy hand is not ſhortened, O Lord, that it cannot help; neither is thine eare ſtopped, that it will not heare: but our miſdoings haue ſeparated vs from thée our God, and our ſinnes haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy face to be hidden from vs. Our hands are defiled with vnrighteouſneſſe, our lippes ſpeake leaſings, our toongs doo ſet out wickedneſſe. No man regardeth righteouſnes, and none iudgeth truelie: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one hopeth in vaine things, and imagineth deceit,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:46"/> conceiueth wearines, &amp; bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth euill. For our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are manie before thée, and our ſinnes doo teſtifie againſt vs, and we acknowledge that we haue doone amiſſe, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing and diſſembling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée, Lord, and fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie from our God, vſing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous imaginations.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, thou art our God, and euerlaſting father, our nouriſher and defender, which wouldeſt not the death of a ſinner, but mercifullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueſt all thoſe, that with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant harts come vnto thée. And now we ſet our eies and face towards thée, lifting vp our hearts vnto thy mercie ſeat, who haſt promiſed to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lode
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6645:46"/> vs, whenſoeuer we come vnto thée. Heare vs therefore, and forgiue vs all our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which we haue committed, from the time of our birth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this preſent houre. O bleſſe vs, and the works alſo of our hands, that we may liue and praiſe thée, world without end, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and ſauiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="prayer">
               <head>17. A praier againſt the enimies of the church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſure ſhips, O Lord, fléete in the ſea vnder their ſailes, and paſſe through the ſtormie tempeſts without drowning: ſo doo thine
<pb facs="tcp:6645:47"/> elect, O God almightie, paſſe through the fearefull perils of all their enimies in this world, by the meanes of thy ſhip the church, and the true faith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; of which ſhip our Sauiour Chriſt is the ſterneman, the guide, and the ſure anchor, to be caſt in all neceſſities, who ſo truſteth in him, ſhalbe brought to the faire hauen of perfect beatitude.</p>
               <p>Who ſo kéepeth him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the boords of his faithfull ſhip, néedeth not to feare the dreadfull dragon, that ſturdie ſtrong Leuiathan, to whoſe power no power on earth may be compared: for he is ſo mad, that he feareth nothing: he is king ouer all the children of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6645:47"/> pride. This is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lucifer, that fell downe from heauen; he is the ſerpent that deceiued in paradiſe, and brought death to all mankind.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, when thy faithfull people are penitent for their offenſes, reſiſt his temptations, and followe thy lawes, putting their whole truſt in thée and thy bleſſed ſonne, then doo they mock and deceiue him; as Chriſt did with his humanitie, which when he thought to deuoure, by tempting the Iewes to put Ieſus to death, he was tripped in his owne turne, and taken into bondage by the vertue of Chriſts diuinitie. And when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we that be his faithfull,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:48"/> be caught (as this our enimie thinketh) in his danger, we turne to our head Ieſus Chriſt for refuge, and by his helpe doo vanquiſh him.</p>
               <p>Great, good Lord, is thy mercie and goodnes, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not thy faithfull to be tempted aboue their ſtrength; but in the midſt of their temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation makeſt a waie for them to eſcape out. The enimie hath no power of himſelfe, but as thou ſuffereſt him; he, with all other creatures, hang vpon thy will &amp; commandements: all wait on thée, that thou maiſt giue them meate in due ſeaſon; when thou giueſt it them, they gather it.</p>
               <p>Thy works Lord are mercie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6645:48"/> and forgiuenes; thou art our iuſtice, whereby thou makeſt vs iuſt, which before were moſt wicked ſinners; thou makeſt vs thine humble creatures, to tremble for feare of thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power and iuſtice: our pride thereby is abated. We account the good déedes, which we haue doone, to be of thy gifts and goodneſſe; nothing preſuming of our owne fraile power: for we knowe that thy holie ſpirit reſteth vpon thoſe that haue a lowly troubled ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and dooe ſtand in awe of thy word.</p>
               <p>The proud and ſtifnecked people dooeſt thou touch with ſcorpions and puniſhments, &amp; then they come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:6645:49"/> of thy Maieſtie; then will they ſaie as <hi>Nabucado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſor</hi> ſaid, after his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Honour and praiſe be vnto thée O God of heauen, whoſe power endureth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wais, and thy kingdome from one generation to another. Then ſhall they be driuen to praiſe thy mightie Maieſtie, as thou art worthie.</p>
               <p>Cruell <hi>Saule</hi> was touched of thy hand, and became <hi>Paule</hi> a welbeloued apoſtle, through the helpe of thy grace, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured more aboundantlie than all other of thine apoſtles; ſuch is the power of thy grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous influence. This thy noble grace ſend me, moſt mercifull God, whereby I ſhall haue a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6645:49"/> louing deſire to honour thée, to praiſe thée, my God and ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſo long as I haue anie being, I will not ceaſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſinnes to thée, and to lament mine iniquities: then ſhall my words be pleſant and acceptable to thée.</p>
               <p>And as I ioie wholie in thée, that art my creator; and in thy ſonne, which is my redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: ſo ſhalt thou alſo delight in me that am thy poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and handie worke, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me the fruit of thy ſonnes paſſion, which he ſuffered for my redemption: to whom, with thée O Father, and the holie Ghoſt, be all honour and glorie, all power and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, now and for euermore, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:50"/> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="prayer">
               <head>18. A praier of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted perſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, thou art iuſt, and all thy works and waies are mercie &amp; truth and thou iudgeſt trulie for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore; remember me, and looke on me O Lord God, and puniſh me not according to my ſinnes, or mine ignorance; but deale with me as it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth beſt vnto thée. And now, O Lord, worke thy will in me, and command my ſpirit to be receiued in peace, that I may be diſſolued of this fowle fleſhie maſſe, thorough the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6645:50"/> which I doo nothing but offend thée my Lord God.</p>
               <p>Yet neuertheleſſe, if it be thy bleſſed will, to giue me lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger life in this vale of miſerie; forgiue me all my ſinnes for Chriſts ſake: for thou art a mercifull God, ſlowe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue wrath, and moſt readie to forgiue. Wherefore extend thy fauour vpon me, O Lord, which ſhall confirme the faith of others. Though I deſerue deſtruction, yet let thy mercie pittie my frailtie: for thou art great, O Lord, for euermore, and thy kingdome is world without end.</p>
               <p>Thou ſcourgeſt and healeſt, thou leadeſt vnto hell, and bringeſt backe againe: and
<pb facs="tcp:6645:51"/> there is none that may eſcape thy hand. O giue thanks vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord ye children of men, for there is none holie, but he; none almightie, but thou O Lord God. Thou haſt chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs for our miſdéeds, and of thine owne mercie ſake thou haſt ſaued vs: wherefore thée will we feare and dread, and magnifie the euerlaſting king in his works.</p>
               <p>As for me and my ſoule, whileſt I liue will I praiſe thy Maieſtie; as long as I haue anie being. For euer ſince I was borne, thou haſt giuen me great cauſe to praiſe thée; for thou haſt béene the defenſe of my iuſt cauſe. Heare now my vehement praier, my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6645:51"/> complaint, and my ſighes which I make before thée this daie, into whoſe holie hands I commit my bodie and ſoule: for thou haſt redéemed me, O thou God of truth, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="prayer">
               <head>19. A praier of the iuſtice of God, and for the aſſistance of Gods ſpirit, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation vpon the Trinitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord I confeſſe thou dooeſt not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me without my deſerts, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will neuer accuſe thée of rigour, as the wicked doo: for I acknowledge that when thou laieſt thy hand heauie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:6645:52"/> anie, there is iuſt cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt ſo entreat them. We are occaſion of our owne perdition, and can pretend no ignorance to excuſe vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: for thou O God calleſt vs by thy word and works, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vertue, and flie vice; which if we bend our ſelues vnto, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending onelie vpon thée, thou haſt promiſed to be our ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter and protectour.</p>
               <p>Thy prouidence, O GOD, dooth not onelie watch ouer thy church in generall, but alſo ouer euerie member thereof: for thy word, O Lord, is eaſie to find, if we haue a deſire therevnto, if we be not blinded by the prince of this world. Thou moſt mightie haſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6645:52"/> both of land and ſea, ſtretch foorth thy mercifull hand to helpe them vp that ſinke, to kéepe them vp that ſtand; for thou art aboue all, and ouer all kingdomes of the earth. Thou haſt made the heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>Lord bow downe thine eare and heare, Lord open thine eies and behold. Our true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and ſuccour in all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and dangers is; to flie vnto thée by moſt earneſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Thou wilt not here, O Lord God, for manie words ſake, or often repetition, but thou dooſt conſider our faith and feruent mind: for thou dooſt looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart of man, and not vpon the outward appearance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:53"/>
               <p>It is great gréefe, O Lord, vnto thy children, when they ſée not the fruits of their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which cauſeth them to thinke, that thou heareſt not: yet dooſt thou but defer them, to cauſe them to praie more earneſtlie and often. For when there ſéemeth to mans iudgement to be no recouerie, but all things are brought to deſpaire, then thou O GOD dooſt ſhew thy mightie power, there is nothing doone without thy prouidence and decrée.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I will call vpon thée with a ſtedfaſt faith, being aſſured of thy mercies; bicauſe I haue found thy helpe at néed in my moſt danger: for thou neuer forſakeſt them that put
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6645:53"/> their truſt in thée, bicauſe of nature thou art verie merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Therefore the faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence thée, and are bold to approch néere thy mightie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; moſt humblie beſéeching thée, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, that thou wilt caſt all our ſinnes behind thy backe; and giue vs thy grace and holie ſpirit, to lead the reſt of our liues in thy feare, dooing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies that is righteous in thy ſight.</p>
               <p>For whoſoeuer walketh in his vocation, and hath the light of God for his guide, née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to feare no danger: thy rodde and thy ſtaffe ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hold him vp. Guide me. O Lord, and giue me the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:6645:54"/> pretious gift of faith, which is the head ſpring of all good works. Baptiſe me inwardlie with the holie Ghoſt, burne and conſume all vice in me, inflame my hart with the loue of thée, and caſt thy fauour vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, O Lord and holie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>So doo likewiſe O Chriſt my Lord and Sauiour, who waſt contented to put off all thy glorie, that thou waſt in before the beginning of the world, to take our nature vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thée, and to ſuffer moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſion vpon the croſſe for our redemption. Waſh me with thy pretious bloud, and make me a choſen veſſell to thy ſelfe: giue me a thankefull
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6645:54"/> hart to praiſe thy name with continuall thankeſgiuing for thy great mercies. Come ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpirit, inſpire my hart with the true knowledge of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the ſonne, procéeding from them both; one God in Trinitie, and Trinitie in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, world without end, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="prayer">
               <head>20. A praier for faith and grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord giue me faith and grace, that I may be wounded in hart to ſéeke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée for mercie: for thou, O God, haſt taught vs in thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie word to looke for aide and
<pb facs="tcp:6645:55"/> helpe of thee in all perils, and that thou art the onlie giuer of victorie in all temptations of our enimies, bodilie &amp; goſtlie. For when thou giueſt ſentence againſt the wicked, they muſt néeds confeſſe thée to be iuſt, and themſelues ſinners. For thou O GOD, which loueſt purenes of hart, &amp; maieſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie deſtroie man, who is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a ſinner: much more wilt thou laie thine hand vpon them, whom thou haſt inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in thy heauenlie wiſdome. Thy fauour O God, is the fountaine of all proſperitie, for thou O Lord dooſt ſtill behold vs. Thée will we reuerence, in what place ſoeuer we be.</p>
               <p>Helpe me therefore, O Lord
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6645:55"/> God, in my good purpoſes, and holie worſhipping, or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thée; and grant vnto me to make a perfect ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and beginning in thée; for I haue bin an vnprofitable ſeruant hitherto. O Lord giue me a mind neuer to ſhew my ſelfe vnthankful for all thy benefits: for thou art the God, which euer hath béene and ſhall be; the GOD almightie, by whom all thinges haue their being; full of mercie, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of thy promiſe. Who ſo ſéeketh any other than thée, O Chriſt, in whom dooth reſt onlie the ſaluation of our ſoules; that creature ſhal find nothing but miſerie and ſorrow. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Lord make me rich in thy
<pb facs="tcp:6645:56"/> fauour and grace, conducting me by thy power. Graft in me a full truſt in thy promiſes for my deliuerance, make me one with thée in euerlaſting loue, that when it ſhall pleaſe thée to call me out of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable world, I may liue with thée and my Sauiour Chriſt, who died for me and all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: whoſe name, with thée O Father, and the holie Ghoſt, be praiſed now and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="prayer">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:6645:56"/>
               <head>21. A praier of the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mankind, of the true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritane, &amp; for ſtrength againſt temptation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Father of heauen, of power almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which with thine onlie word diddeſt create and make all the whole world, and all for the profit &amp; ſeruice of man, whom thou diddeſt create of all other a moſt noble and perfect crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, giuing him power vpon earth, the waters, and all the fowles and birds of the aire; thou madeſt him alſo after thine own ſimilitude and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, induing him with a
<pb facs="tcp:6645:57"/> reaſonable ſoule, and all the powers thereof, thou alſo did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt put him in the pleaſant garden of paradiſe, excepting nothing from him, but the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the onlie trée of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill: and further, for his helpe, comfort, and companie, of a ribbe of his ſide thou madeſt for him a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and gaueſt hir to him to be his wife.</p>
               <p>There had they inſtructions giuen them, and the lawe of life for an heritage. Before them was laid both life and death, good and euill, with a fréewill giuen them to take which liked them beſt. But their frailtie was ſuch, that they, through a ſmall intiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6645:57"/> choſe the euill, and left the good: they left life, &amp; choſe death. Thus Lord, through ſin, &amp; breaking of thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, man loſt the fréewill that was giuen him in his creation, and purchaſed death to all his poſteritie.</p>
               <p>In the waie as he went to Ieruſalem and Iericho, he fell in the hands of théeues, who hurting and wounding him ſore, departed, leauing him halfe dead; ſo that he could haue helpe of none, but only of the good Samaritan, who, as he paſſed by the ſame waie, powred wine and oile into his wounds, and tooke the cure of him.</p>
               <p>This onlie Samaritan was
<pb facs="tcp:6645:58"/> thy deare Sonne Chriſt, which tooke vpon him all the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of mankind, and laid them on his backe by his death, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and clenſing him, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie from the originall ſin of our father <hi>Adam,</hi> but alſo from all our ſins which we commit from time to time, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his paſſion, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of baptiſme vpon our repentance. For as by <hi>Adam,</hi> death came to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſo by Ieſus Chriſt was mankind reſtored to life.</p>
               <p>For this great and high be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thy ſonnes bleſſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for our redemption, we thy poore creatures praiſe and thanke thée, moſt humblie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his ineſtimable
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6645:58"/> loue towards vs, in that thou vouchſafedſt to die for vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then ſinners, &amp; thy mortall enimies. Neuertheleſſe, moſt mercifull father, we are of our ſelues not able to do any thing that good is, no not ſo much as to thinke a good thought, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thine aid and aſſiſtance. We wander here miſerablie, in the lowe parts of the vile earth; our ſtrength will not ſerue vs to clime to the high of the hilles, where thou dwelleſt in thy mount Sion, a place prepared for thine elect, a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen inheritance of thy faithfull ſeruant <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his ſéed.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſince we, being burthened with the affects of
<pb facs="tcp:6645:59"/> worldlie pleaſures, and alſo with other cares and troubles, can by no meanes aſcend to thée, that art on the top of ſo high a mountaine, (ſo manie legions of angels attending on thy Maieſtie) we haue no remedie, but with the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> now to lift the eies of our harts and minds towards thée, &amp; to crie for helpe to come down from thée to vs thy poore and wretched ſeruants.</p>
               <p>We wander here below, as loſt ſhéepe, hauing no ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard; we are aſſailed on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide with manifold eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; the diuell rauening and hungering, ſéeketh whom he may deuoure; the world allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs alſo to hir deceitfull va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6645:59"/> our fleſh alſo, which we carrie about vs, is our enimie readie and prone to drawe vs vnto all vices and pleaſures. From this can we by no meanes be defended, but by thée Lord.</p>
               <p>Send vs therfore thy helpe and holie angell, to aſſiſt and ſtrengthen vs: for of thée moſt mercifull Father floweth all bountie and goodnes. Thou O Lord God madeſt heauen and earth for thine honour, and mans commoditie; eſtabliſh therefore good Lord the choſen works of thy hand with thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall helpe: from heauen ſend vs downe the welſpring of thy grace, and thy ſtrong angell to aide vs by his helpe,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:60"/> that no aſſault of our ſpirituall enimies doo preuaile againſt vs: but from all euils by thy word defend vs, Lord, both touching the bodie, and alſo the ſoule, that no temptation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt béene our protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, euen from our mothers wombe; and our truſt is that thou wilt ſo continue all the daies of our life, and ſpeciallie at the houre of our death, that we may aſcend to the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ieruſalem, where we ſhall reaſt in the boſome of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abraham,</hi> the father of all faithfull beléeuers, there to praiſe thée, and thy louing Sonne, and the holie Ghoſt, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="prayer">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:6645:60"/>
               <head>22. A praier and thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing vnto God, for his manifold gifts, with an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſinne, and pardon for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Praiſe the Lord our God for euer, and let vs giue thanks vnto the name of his glorie, which excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all other thankeſgiuings and praiſes: for thou art our God alone, thou haſt made the heauen of all heauens, with all the hoſte of them; the earth, and all the creatures, which liue by thée; the ſea, and all that moue therein: thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueſt them all through thine
<pb facs="tcp:6645:61"/> omnipotent power. For the which all the hoſt of heauen praiſeth thée, and we thy poore children here on earth doo crie vnto thée; Holie, holie, holie, art thou, which euer was, and euer ſhall be, O Lord God of ſabaoth.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt made good all thy words and promiſes, for thou art righteous and true, and haſt conſidered the miſerie of our forefathers: for they were ſtubborne againſt thée, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding thy precepts and commandements, neither were mindfull of thy wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous works that thou diddeſt for them, whoſe footeſteps we are prone and readie to follow in all vngodlines, in theſe our
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6645:61"/> daies: but thou O Lord art mercifull, patient, and of great goodnes, and forſakeſt vs not whenſoeuer we returne vnto thée.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, O Lord, heare vs from heauen, and forgiue vs all our vnthankfulnes, and giue vs faithfull hearts to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe thy commandements; which if we doo, we ſhall liue in them. For it is not in mans power to order his owne waies, nor to rule his owne ſteps or goings: therefore cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten thou vs, O Lord, but with fauor, not in thy wrath. Bring vs not vtterlie to naught, for we haue none other ſauiour, neither can we helpe our ſelues; for by our ſaluation
<pb facs="tcp:6645:62"/> thy name ſhall be praiſed.</p>
               <p>Therefore Lord helpe vs, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of thy mercie thou haſt made vs a moſt deare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion vnto thée, and we through our ſinnes are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie puniſhed. Declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thy loue, and finiſh the worke that thou haſt begunne in vs; ſo ſhall we liue and praiſe thy holie name for euer &amp; euer, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="prayer">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6645:62"/>
               <head>23. A praier wherein the hart poureth out it ſelfe before God, with humble ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and chriſtian lowlines in diuers conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſt pleaſant thing that I can offer vnto thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, O Lord, is to giue thée a thankfull heart for all thy benefits, and to be inwardlie ſorie that euer I did anie thing which ſhould offend thée; then, to mortifie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of the fleſh, to put off the old Adam, and put on Chriſt; to leaue to be carnall, and to become ſpirituall. Wherefore I will call on thy
<pb facs="tcp:6645:63"/> holie name, for thy gratious aid and aſſiſtance; to helpe me and ſtrengthen me in theſe my good purpoſes, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but thou wilt moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie heare me.</p>
               <p>My heart and my whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, I offer willinglie vnto thy ſeruice, which although it be of ſmall value in déed; yet I doo not miſtruſt but it ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted in thy ſight: as was the offring of two mites, which the poore woman threw into the treaſurie at Ieruſalem, which ſmall ſumme of hir pouertie thou diddeſt more eſtéeme and praiſe, than all the great gifts of the rich men.</p>
               <p>I humblie beſéech thy high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to accept this gift of my
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6645:63"/> poore ſoule &amp; bodie, which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of my louing mind towards thée; and vouchſafe Lord ſo to worke in them by thy grace, that they may will and worke that which may be acceptable in thy ſight: ſo that I may truelie performe my vowes made vnto thée, by kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thy lawes and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements with my whole hart, which I and euerie true chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an profeſſe to kéepe. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he be that breaketh but one of them, is guiltie of all.</p>
               <p>It is not in mans power to turne to thée O God, but thy worke onelie to conuert vs: for we conſider thy Maieſtie, and the weakneſſe of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh. Thy mercie worketh
<pb facs="tcp:6645:64"/> in vs ſorrowe and repentance for our former life. All things are gouerned by thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence O God; if thou bleſſe vs, all creatures ſhall fauour vs. Let thy holie ſpirit counſell me how to come foorth of this carefull and troubleſome life, that I may hide my ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadowe of thy wings, where I know I ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by thy power, which ſhall be a ſigne of thy fatherlie care towards me. Wherefore I will reſigne my ſelfe wholie vnto thée, truſting in thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
               <p>Thou O God art onelie the true felicitie, to heale me thou art able, and to raiſe me to life, though I were dead long ago,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6645:64"/> and turned to duſt. For I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thée to be almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and that there is nothing done on earth without thy will and ordinance: wherefore I will not truſt to anie worldlie helpe. In the daies of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thou kéepeſt couenant and mercie with thy ſeruants that walke before thée with all their heart; and though thou correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt from time to time, yet thy helpe will not be farre off, if we returne to thée.</p>
               <p>Thy mercie is great to poore ſinners; for thou art more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to pardon them with long ſuffering, rather than to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them. Thou ſheweſt fauor towards the fatherleſſe, which walke after thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:6645:65"/> as thou art God, and creator of the ſoule and body, ſo wouldeſt thou haue vs ſerue thée with both, and that thy people be continuallie ſubiect vnto thée. For the greater gifts that we receiue at thy mercifull hands O Lord God, and the higher that thou dooeſt preferre vs, the more are we bound to praiſe thée for the ſame. And though we be high or lowe in degrée, yet can we not be exempted from dooing our duties.</p>
               <p>Thou O God art the giuer of all good things: wherfore I am readie to beſtowe all that I haue at thy commandement. Giue me grace, O Lord God, that I neuer prouoke thée to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6645:65"/> anger by my ſinnes, that thou maiſt mitigate thy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments towards me, &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me with thy holie ſpirit, that I may leade an vpright life, with true faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, vnto the glorie of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie name, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="prayer">
               <head>24. A praier wherein the afflicted perſon praieth againſt his enimies, that God would turne vpon them his iudgements.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God of our fathers, helpe me poore deſolate cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, I beſéech thée: for thou haſt don al things
<pb facs="tcp:6645:66"/> from the beginning; and looke what thine euerlaſting coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell hath deuiſed, it came euer to paſſe: for all thy waies are prepared, and thy iudgements are doone in thine euerlaſting foreknowledge. O looke thou now vpon mine enimies, and bring to paſſe, O Lord, that the pride of them may be cut downe: for thy power ſtandeth not in the iudgement of men. For there was neuer proud perſon that pleaſed thée; but in the praier of the humble and méeke hath thy pleaſure béene euermore.</p>
               <p>O thou God of the heauens, thou maker and Lord of all creatures, heare and helpe me calling vpon thée, and putting
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6645:66"/> my truſt in thy mercie: for I haue none other helper but thée O Lord God. Thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and ſhew thy ſelfe vnto me, in the time of my diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and troubles, ſtrengthen me with patience in all aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. Thou Lord of all power knoweſt all things. O thou mightie God aboue all, heare the voice of them that haue none other hope but onlie thée; deliuer me out of the hands of mine enimies, and make me not a ſcorne vnto the fooliſh.</p>
               <p>Heare thou my God, for I am deſpiſed; turne their ſhame vpon their owne heads: for they are puft vp with pride, as the ſtomach that is choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with fat. O Lord of hoſts,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:67"/> thou righteous ſearcher, which knoweſt the reines and the verie heart; let me ſée them puniſhed, if it be thy will: for vnto thée doo I commit my cauſe. For though they wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlie prouoked me to doo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill for euill, yet thy word kept me backe: for I behaued my ſelfe vprightlie towards mine enimies. Therefore I humblie beſéech thée, let them knowe that thou art the defender of my iuſt cauſe.</p>
               <p>Let my perſecutors be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, but not me; thou ſhalt bring vpon them the time of their plague, and ſhalt deſtroie them right ſoone. Wherefore O Lord my ſauiour, let the ſame ſhame and confuſion light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6645:67"/> them, which they intended to haue brought vpon me, and bicauſe thou haſt all things in thy hands and power, thou wilt ſpéedilie reward them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their deſeruings: for the deapth of thy prouidence go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth all things, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them as it pleaſeth thée.</p>
               <p>Good Lord make me not a mocking ſtocke vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, nor wrap me vp with the deceitfull, when they are put to ſhame: for ſéeing my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles come of thy appointment, I will with thy helpe indure them with patience, for I put not my truſt in anie worldlie thing, but in thée O God my maker and defender. I will ſerue thée with a pure affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:68"/> and with the godlie that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thée in ſpirit and truth: which that I may the better fulfil, bleſſe me with thy grace, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="prayer">
               <head>25. A praier for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of faith, wherein alſo the vnmeaſurable loue of God the Father is recorded.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Mercifull GOD, that art ſo good and louing a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make me heire of thy heauenlie king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with thy bleſſed ſonne Ieſus Chriſt; increaſe my faith in thée O Lord, that I may moſt faith fullie beléeue all that thou haſt commanded in thy
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6645:68"/> holie word: for whatſoeuer is not of faith, the ſame is ſinne. Faith is the ſure and perfect foundation of all chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, wherby thy faithfull hope ſurelie, that all thy promiſes made vnto them of thy méere goodnes and liberalitie, ſhall ſurelie, and vndoubtedlie be fulfilled. Heauen and earth ſhall periſh, rather than thy word and promiſe ſhalbe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfourmed.</p>
               <p>By faith <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and by faith he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to make ſacrifice of his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie begotten ſonne <hi>Iſaac.</hi> Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that were faithfull did our Sauiour worke his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, in ſo much that in his countrie of Galilie he did not
<pb facs="tcp:6645:69"/> manie, bicauſe of their vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léef. And by this faith, with the helpe of thy grace at this daie, and to the end of the world, are and ſhall all thy choſen people be ſaued, and that fréelie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie deſeruing of theirs.</p>
               <p>And being fullie perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thy holie ſcripture, I beléeue in thée my moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, thrée perſons in one eſſence, and in all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in thy holie word; and the ſame faith I will not let to confeſſe before all the world. I will not doo as manie of the Iewes did, which beléeued on thy ſonne, yet durſt they not boldlie confeſſe him, neither make their faith known, leaſt they ſhould haue béene expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6645:69"/> out of the ſynagog. They more eſtéemed the glorie of this world, than they did eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téeme the glorie of God.</p>
               <p>But through the helpe of thy grace, Lord, I will ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that I firmelie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue, and that which I doo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue; I will by no meanes hide, but ſpeake boldlie: for I know, that who ſo dooth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thée before men, him wilt thou confeſſe before thy father which is in heauen. Faith cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me to loue thée for thine own ſake, aboue all creatures. Loue cauſeth me to confeſſe thée before all the world, and for thy ſake to worke towards my neighbour, as thou haſte commanded me. It is thy
<pb facs="tcp:6645:70"/> grace that maketh man vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and good, which grace is the nurſe of all good things: it leadeth man from one vertue to another; it kéepeth vs from falling, lifting vs vp againe when we are fallen. Thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe hath béen from euerlaſting, and endureth for euer.</p>
               <p>What ſhall I giue againe vnto thée O Lord, for thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold benefits, that thou haſt doone vnto me? Great cauſe haue I to be thankfull, when I remember thy tender loue, ſhewed vnto man, in his firſt creation, next in power, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, knowledge, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the nature of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, made alſo touching the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6645:70"/> ſoule like vnto thine owne i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; which he through frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie did abuſe: yet neuertheles, thou of thy mercifull pitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing that this noble worke of thine ſhould not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie be loſt, diddeſt ſend thine onelie begotten ſonne to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come man, and wiledſt him to ſuffer death for mans redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>What more loue could be ſhewed than thou haſt ſhewed? what more could be doon to thy vineyard than thou haſt doone? thy charitie was feruent to vs when we were all ſinners; few men would now die for their righteous fréend, but thou ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedſt thy ſonne to ſuffer death for thine enimies, that were
<pb facs="tcp:6645:71"/> ſinners: yea, when we dailie now doo fall ſtill from thée, by committing all kind of vices; yet dooeſt thou mercifullie ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vs, and gentlie receiue vs, ſo oft as we do returne againe to thée by repentance.</p>
               <p>We forgiue our neighbours ſcarſelie one or twiſe, when they diſpleaſe vs: but thou Lord forgiueſt vs, not ſeuen times, but ſeuentie times ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that is, ſo often as we fal. Euen ſo willeſt thou vs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue one another. Wherefore, Lord, reach vnto me thy hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand, as thou diddeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Peter;</hi> and as he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made able to walke vpon the water, ſo ſhall I be able thereby to performe thy holie
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6645:71"/> lawe, which my hart is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to doo in the preſence of all the congregation, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may take example by my dooings, and glorifie thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie for thy noble gifts.</p>
               <p>Strengthen me, Lord, with thy holie ſpirit; giue me an hart and will rather to chooſe to ſuffer death, than to breake anie of them: for right deare in thy ſight is the death of thy ſaints. Thy name will I call vpon, and honour it all the daies of my life. I will alſo, as I haue promiſed, fulfill my vowes that I haue made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée. I will giue vp my ſelfe to thée, as an oblation; and ſéeing I am thy image, I will declare vnto the holie congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:72"/> how mercifullie thou haſt receiued me to thy grace. I will honor thée in thy church, wherof I am partaker, through the meanes of thy ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, my onelie Lord and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="prayer">
               <head>26. A praier vnto God the father, wherein the ſinner ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his greefe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD I am not worthie of the leaſt of thy mercies and truth, which thou haſt ſhewed vnto me thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant: for though thou haſt, O Lord aſſaide me with the one hand, thou haſt euer holden me
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6645:72"/> vp with the other: for thou art euer preſent with vs, to ſuccor vs in our troubles. And if thou O God diddeſt not open our eies, we could neither ſée, nor vſe the meanes, which thou haſt ſet before vs. As for me, when thou openedſt mine eies and heart, I was readie to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beie thée, being aſſured, that I was written in the booke of thine elect to this end: for thy prouidence watcheth alwaies to direct thy children, that they ſlide not.</p>
               <p>Wherefore now, O Lord, call to remembrance the cares and gréefes which we haue ſuffered; conſider and ſée our confuſion. Our inheritance is turned vnto ſtrangers, we
<pb facs="tcp:6645:73"/> are become carefull and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe; our parents, which now are gone, haue ſinned, and we muſt beare their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Alas that they and we haue ſinned ſo ſore! There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is our hart full of heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but thou O Lord that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineſt euermore, and thy ſeat world withou end, doo not forget vs.</p>
               <p>Let all the world ſée thy iudgements, in that thou art our God, and ruler ouer all: which we will euer confeſſe, bicauſe thou art ſo glorious; and through thy mercifull aid I will remaine ſtedfaſt, being vpholden by thy power O GOD. For I haue euer this hope of conſcience, that thou
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6645:73"/> wilt not impute vnto me my ignorance. Wherefore grant vnto me from hencefoorth, to liue in thy feare all the daies of my life, and to end this pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in faith and truth, to the glorie of thy holie name. Which grant vs, O deare father, for thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake, who is bleſſed with thée O father. To whom with thée, and the holie Ghoſt, be giuen all honour &amp; praiſe, world without end, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:74"/>
               <head>27. A praier vnto the ſonne of God, wherein the ſoule is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, by the rehearſall of Chriſts manifold benefits.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> My ſoule, inforce thée with all thy ſtrength to ſet foorth the noble praiſes of the Lord thy GOD and redéemer. Thou haſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thée manie goodlie gifts of nature and grace, which giue thée occaſion neuer to ceaſe from giuing of thanks. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not theſe beneficiall gifts, which he hath giuen thée: for of forgetfulneſſe commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnthankefulneſſe; which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindnes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6645:74"/> maketh thée not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to enioie that is giuen thée. Conſider my ſoule, firſt, the miſerable eſtate wherein thou waſt brought by ſinne.</p>
               <p>Thou waſt the enimie of God, the bond-ſeruant of the diuell, and ſubiect to death e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. From this hath thy mercifull brother Ieſus Chriſt, being both GOD and man, deliuered thée, making ſatiſfaction for all thy ſinnes, through his death and paſſion. What greater loue could he ſhewe, than to die for thée, whereby he driueth awaie all thine offenſes.</p>
               <p>If thou ſet before thine eies the multitude of thy ſinnes, then ſhalt thou alſo behold the
<pb facs="tcp:6645:75"/> benefits and goodnes of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer. Giue him therefore the ſacrifice of praiſe, and glorifie him; for therein he delighteth: not for his profit, but for thine; not for that he is anie thing thereby aduanced, but that doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy dutie by faith, thou maiſt be made partaker of ioie euerlaſting with him.</p>
               <p>And though he ſend thée ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie aduerſities in this world, thinke that he loueth thée: for if he did not, he would leaue thée to ſinke in thine owne ſinne, to the vtter loſſe both of bodie and ſoule. But he hath ſaued thy life from euerlaſting deſtruction, he hath redéemed thée with his moſt pretious blood, he died for thy ſinnes, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6645:75"/> roſe againe for thy iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Loue him therefore my ſoule, and magnifie him all the daies of thy life. Put thy whole affiance in him, and feare no violence of enimies: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they aſſault thée, yet can they not vanquiſh thée.</p>
               <p>For he, that through his mercie and louing kindneſſe, hath giuen thée power by him to vanquiſh thine enimies; will not faile, after thy fight and victorie, to reward thée with a crowne of glorie and immortalitie. When death thy laſt enimie ſhall be ouercome, then ſhalt thou be admitted to the ioifull companie of angels and ſaints in heauen, there to haue more ioie and comfort
<pb facs="tcp:6645:76"/> than hart can wiſh. When the glorie of the Lord ſhall appeare then ſhalt thou be fullie ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to thy contentation. His countenance ſhall repleniſh thée with all io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</p>
               <p>Wherfore my ſoule, whileſt thou art in this preſent life, ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thy fraile and heauie carcaſe, giue thanks louinglie to thy gentle redéemer, for his vnſpeakeable kindneſſe. His grace is readie at hand at thy call, fight therefore manfullie and mightilie, againſt all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full concupiſcence and vice; put off the old man, and leaue all the works of darkenes; put on the new man, &amp; arme thée with the armor of light.</p>
               <p>Beginne a new life, and flie
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6645:76"/> vnto Chriſt the ſtrong tower and ſure rocke; leaue all worldlie pleaſures and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and call for his grace, and doubt not but he will make thée liue a new ſpirituall life, and giue thée immortallitie both of ſoule and bodie in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen euerlaſtinglie, where thou ſhalt continuallie behold the face of God, to the fulneſſe of all thy ioie and contentation.</p>
               <p>Stand faſt in this hope, and miſtruſt not the mercies of GOD; call to remembrance the ancient goodnes of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father, which is all one with the mercie of his ſonne and the holie Ghoſt. Behold how mercifull and beneficiall he hath euer bin to thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:6645:77"/> beléeue and truſt in him. For looke how high the heauen is from the earth, ſo great is his mercie alſo to them that feare him.</p>
               <p>How much are we bound to ſerue this our God in Chriſt, by whom we haue receiued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption? He is a God of all gods, mightie and terrible, which accepteth no perſons, nor taketh rewards. Thou dooſt right vnto the fatherleſſe, and helpeſt the ſtranger that is in diſtreſſe. Come vnto me moſt louing God and ſauiour, helpe and fight thou for me; let not mine enimies haue the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ouer me.</p>
               <p>Powre foorth thy grace vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my corrupt nature, and I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6645:77"/> ſhall be purged from all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. I am almoſt dead in ſinne; quicken me, and giue me life againe, ſithence thou art God the author of life and health: for none can doo it but thou alone, my God and ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; then ſhall my toong praiſe thy righteouſneſſe, O Lord God, without ceaſing, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="prayer">
               <head>28. Another praier vnto the ſonne, wherein the miſeries of this our mortall life are remembred.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt louing Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that art the verie naturall ſonne of the almightie heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:78"/> father, God of God, light of light, a God thou art without beginning, a Lord from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, before the mountains were brought foorth, or euer the earth and the world were made, whoſe kingdome like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhall endure world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Thou Lord (I ſaie) that art equall with thy father in power and glorie, dideſt not diſdaine to become man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, to the intent thou wouldeſt by ſuffering painfull paſſion, be the refuge of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, from one generation to another.</p>
               <p>The yoong chickens, when the kite ſtriketh at them, haue none other refuge but to run dickering vnder the wings of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6645:78"/> the hen: no more hath man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind anie other defenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his rauening enimies, but onelie the couering of thy grace, and the ſhadowe of thy moſt pretious paſſion; which is vnto vs a ſtrong tower, and ſure ſhield of defenſe againſt all inuaſions.</p>
               <p>This grace, mercifull Lord, we humblie beſéech thée to ſend vs, that by turning thy fauourable countenance vpon vs, we may knowe our owne infirmities; and leauing all pleaſure in vile temporall things, we may turne to thée that art our Sauiour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer, our God and our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Make vs to knowe in what
<pb facs="tcp:6645:79"/> miſerie, in what trouble, and in how manie kind of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures we lead our liues here continuallie, vntill the time that age or ſickneſſe commeth vpon vs; at which time thou wilt call vs, ſaieng; Ye chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Adam,</hi> returne ye now againe into the earth from whence ye came. This is the debt due vnto nature. Of earth we came, in the earth we trauell, of earth we liue, and into earth me muſt returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>For the life of man is to be likened vnto a night watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that when his houre is paſt, taketh his reſt. Thus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it by the life of man, who firſt paſſeth awaie his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6645:79"/> next in youth, the third in manhood, the fourth in age, which vaniſheth awaie like ſmoke that paſſeth awaie out of the chimneie. For as ſoone as men begin to liue, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to die; as ſoone as thy pleſure is, Lord, to haue them, they fade awaie ſuddenlie like the graſſe, which is in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning gréene, and growing, and in the euening it is cut downe and withered.</p>
               <p>In youth we are pleaſant and merrie, luſtie and ſtrong, ſpringing vp gréene as dooth the corne: but when harueſt commeth, it ripeth, and withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and is cut downe. When age commeth, the body of man drieth awaie; then death ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh
<pb facs="tcp:6645:80"/> vs. All this remembred, who can take anie comfort? who can be merrie, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth the laſt end? for we bring our yeares to an end, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a tale that is tould. Wherefore teach vs, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſt, to number our daies, that we may applie our harts vnto wiſedome.</p>
               <p>Giue vs grace to haue in remembrance the ſhort daies of our life, with the dangerous paſſage of our time in this world: ſo that hauing no truſt or affiance in the vncertaintie thereof, we may wholie applie our ſelues to the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy heauenlie wiſdome; that we may conſider earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thy goodneſſe ſhewed vnto
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6645:80"/> vs, who art the power and the wiſdome of God thy father.</p>
               <p>Behold Lord our hartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for our ſinnes, we beſéech thée, turne thy mercie and louing kindneſſe vnto vs, be gratious to vs that are thy ſeruants: for although we fall often times from thée, through frailtie of our nature; yet we forſake thée not vtterlie, but return to thée, as the prodigall ſonne returned to his father after long abſence, &amp; was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued &amp; well accepted of. We are thy ſeruants, redie to ſerue thée by the helpe of thy grace.</p>
               <p>Heare therefore our humble petition, which is, to craue thy mercie and grace: with the ſame ſatiſfie my ſoule, moſt
<pb facs="tcp:6645:81"/> gratious Lord, for the which all thy faithfull doo ſore hunger and thirſt, ſo long as they abide in this life, but they ſhall be perfectlie and faithfullie moſt fullie ſatiſfied, when thy glorie ſhall be manifeſt vnto them in thy heauenlie habitation.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall we reioiſe and be glad all the daies of our life. With that ioifull daie comfort vs, good Lord, in recompenſe of the yeares wherein we haue ſuffered much aduerſitie. Let thy grace ſhine vpon vs, let it euer aſſiſt vs, O mercifull Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, which art the bright light of God thy father. Then ſhall we proſper in this world, and after follow thée the lambe, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thou goeſt: which grant
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6645:81"/> for thy mercie ſake. To thée, with the Father, and the holie Ghoſt, be praiſe and glorie, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="prayer">
               <head>29. A praier vnto the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, wherein his glorie is confeſſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Holie Ghoſt, thou art my ſtrength, power, and refuge in time of my trouble: thou diddeſt helpe me in my youth, when I had more ſtrength; helpe me now, good Lord, ſo much the more in my old age and weakenes, for the depth of thy prouidence gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all things. Thou art the Lord of life, whoſe throne is moſt excellent, with God the
<pb facs="tcp:6645:82"/> Father and the Sonne, which dwelleſt in the place of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reſt. Thou art the comfort of thine elect, and the ſeuenfold diſpoſer of the works of God. All they that forſake thée ſhall be confounded, and they that depart from thée ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in earth, bicauſe they haue forſaken the Lord of life.</p>
               <p>Turne ye therefore all ye ſinners, and doo righteouſnes before God, and be ye ſure that his holie ſpirit will not depart from you. For he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the praier of <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he was entreated for the wicked Sodomites, if there could haue béene found ten righteous in the citie: how much more wilt thou grant the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6645:82"/> praiers of the godlie, when they call vpon thée, either for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or for the preſeruation of thy church? Wherefore, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art iuſt, O Lord, lead me out of the danger of mine enimies: for vnto thée doo I make my praier, O thou moſt high poſſeſſer of heauen and earth. Be not terrible vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, O Lord: for thou art God my comforter, in whom I hope, when I am in perill. O thou finger of GOD, touch my heart, and vnloſe the ſame from all worldlie vanitie.</p>
               <p>Inſpire me with thy grace, that I may confeſſe the father and the ſonne, with thée O ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt, to be one GOD in perſons thrée, and euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:6645:83"/> in vnitie; who guideſt and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneſt the world, through thy omnipotencie, whoſe mercies be praiſed for all thy benefits, in the world of worlds, now and for euermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="prayer">
               <head>30. A praier in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of death, wherein the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of riches is touched, and the reuelation and reward of mens works is promiſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ake vs, O Lord, to remember our end, wherevnto all men by nature muſt come: then ſhall we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doo amiſſe. Inſtruct our harts in thy godlie wiſedome, that we may applie our time according to thy holie worde and will. Defend vs from the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6645:83"/> ſnares of our wicked enimie the diuell. Let vs not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with the wicked mammon of this deteſtable world, nor boaſt our ſelues in the multitude of our riches, for they and we ſhall fade and fall awaie, as the freſh flower that kéepeth his colour and ſwéet ſauour for a ſhort ſpace, but the heate of the ſunne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it wither, his beautie to periſh, and his flower to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie. Euen ſo ſhall it be with all ſuch as put their truſt in their riches; they ſhall periſh togither with their aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; their goods maie ſerue them here for a ſhort ſpace, but no man can with monie win his brother from death, or
<pb facs="tcp:6645:84"/> make agréement vnto God for him, for it coſt more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeme their ſoules, ſo that they muſt let that alone foreuer.</p>
               <p>Onelie thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt was our redemption, which price if it well not ſerue the wicked, for that they end in ſinne, our ſauiour will not paie for them a ſecond death to redéeme them withall, but leue them to be tormented for euer. Wherefore giue vs grace Lord, that we may laie vp our riches in the hands of Chriſt, the ſure treſure houſe, that is, in the hands of the poore; that we may be ſure to find it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with greater gaine, when we depart out of this wretched world: ſo ſhall we lay vp
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6645:84"/> temporall things, and receiue againe eternall.</p>
               <p>For if we will be rich in good works, and readie to giue and to diſtribute, we ſhall laie vp for vs a good foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time to come: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariewiſe, the wicked, which are now here in great glorie; whoſe dwelling is in the night, their works are hid, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péere not; but at the great iudgement, when Chriſt which is our life ſhall ſhew himſelfe, then ſhall the iuſt appéere with him alſo in glorie; then ſhall it be cléere day-light, all mens works ſhall appéere as they be.</p>
               <p>The trée that in the winter ſheweth no freſhneſſe, ſhall then receiue ſap from the root,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:85"/> &amp; appéere beautifull, where the flower and herbe that was in ſight pleaſant for a while ſhall wither awaie and fall. Then ſhal the ſtrength of the wicked conſume, hell ſhall be their dwelling in perpetuall moor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Thus wilt thou deſtroie all the vngodlie, yet haue wée a ſure hope thou wilt deliuer our ſoules from the power of hell, and receiue vs to thée by grace, here in this world; and after, when thou ſhalt come to the laſt iudgement, to take vs to thy ſelfe in glorie; that where thou art, there may we be with thée. For we are not gréeued at the vngodlie, nor afraid when they be made rich, and the glorie of their houſes
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6645:85"/> increaſed. We knowe that their honour indureth but a ſmall ſeaſon, &amp; vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie as dooth the ſmoke; for thou regardeſt them not: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou giueſt them things of ſmall eſtimation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> gaue gifts to the ſonnes of his concubines, and ſent them awaie; but vnto <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> he gaue his poſſeſſions, and all that he had: ſo Lord, to the wicked thou giueſt tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, but for thy faithfull thou reſerueſt thy euerlaſting heauenlie inheritance. This is a ſure and permanent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the othee ſoone ſlippeth awaie; their time here is but ſhort, and when they die, they ſhall carrie nothing awaie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:86"/> with them, neither ſhall their pompe followe them. For thou O Lord wilt driue them awaie.</p>
               <p>As wax melteth at the heat of the fire, ſo ſhall the vngodlie periſh at thy preſence; then ſhalt thou change their honour into ſhame: for while they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, they were counted happie men, and ſo long as they were in proſperitie, men ſpake good of them; but when they followe their fathers generation, they ſhall neuer ſée light any more. They were the children of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, come of a wicked proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, they haue followed their forefathers ſteps, their déedes were euill, they loued darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe better than light. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6645:86"/> they ſhall haue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting darknes with torments, they ſhall haue fire, but it ſhall giue them no comfortable heat.</p>
               <p>Theſe paines are ordained for them that were in honour, and had riches in aboundance, and did forget their eſtate, and for lacke of knowledge were led into captiuitie. Wherefore O good God, let vs not be of the number of them; but build vs vpon thy bleſſed ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the head corner ſtone: in him whoſoeuer is builded, groweth vnto an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie temple in the Lord his God. For of our ſelues we haue hard harts to beléeue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou write thy law in our
<pb facs="tcp:6645:87"/> harts by thy holie ſpirit. Now is the acceptable time; Lord let vs find grace and fauour in thy ſight, pardon our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes and ſinne, and take vs to thine inheritance, that we may reigne with thée in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for euer and euer, Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="prayer">
               <head>31. A praier that we may heare the word of God and keepe it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am thy ſeruant, Lord, giue me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that I may learne thy lawe and decrées: incline my ſoule to the words of thy mouth, bicauſe thy talke flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6645:87"/> like vnto dew. The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lits ſaid vnto <hi>Moſes;</hi> Speake thou vnto vs, and we will heare ſhée, but let not the Lord ſpeake, leaſt we die. Howbeit, I praie not ſo, O Lord, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> I doo humblie and earneſtlie beſéech thée thus; Speake on Lord, for thy ſeruant dooth hearken, for thou art the giuer and inſpirer of life, who art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without anie to inſtruct me.</p>
               <p>Thy Miniſters ſpeake for thée thy ſecreats, but thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockeſt the vnderſtanding of the things pronounced; they rehearſe to vs thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, but it is thy aid and helpe that giueth ſtrength to
<pb facs="tcp:6645:88"/> walke ouer the ſame, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt light vnto the minds. Wherefore, bicauſe thou art the euerlaſting truth, ſpeake thou Lord my God vnto me, leaſt I die, and be made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull: for thou haſt the words of euerlaſting life. Speake therefore that thing, which may bring both comfort vnto my ſoule, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto my life, and alſo may cauſe glorie and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall honor vnto thée. For man dooth periſh, but thy truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth, O God, for euer.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are they therefore, whom thou inſtructeſt and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt knowledge vnto O Lord, and dooſt teach thy lawe, that thou maiſt helpe them in time
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6645:88"/> of trouble, that they periſh not. Looke fauourablie vpon me, O GOD, and grant (I praie thée) that thy truth may teach me, kéepe me, and bring me vnto a happie end. Let the ſame deliuer me from all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked luſts, and from inordinate loue. Thou haſt infinit means, and all creatures are at thy commandement; therefore good Lord ſhewe ſome ſigne, whereby I ſhall be deliuered, and ſend thine holie angell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, to kéepe me in thy waie, and to bring me to the place which thou haſt prouided for me, that I may liue with thée euerlaſtinglie, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:89"/>
               <head>32. A praier wherein the word of God is praiſed, and what things are thereby to be wrought &amp; accompliſhed, his mercie and iuſtice alſo is heare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Rant me, good Lord, to ſerue thée with a perfect hart and willing mind: for thou Lord ſercheſt the hart, and vnderſtandeſt all our i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations and thoughts. If we ſéeke thée, thou wilt be found; but if we forſake thée, thou wilt caſt vs off for euer. If we depend onelie vpon thée O God, we ſhall not néed to be troubled with theſe worldlie
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6645:89"/> reſpects: for thou wilt giue vs at all times that which ſhall be neceſſarie for bodie and ſoule; if we feare thée, and obeie thy holie word, which thou wilt haue found true, and alſo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified for thine owne honour and glorie, and for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</p>
               <p>Vpon thée therefore will I ſtill call, truſting that thou wilt ſhortlie heare and helpe me; I will alſo call vpon the mightie name of thy ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in whoſe name the faithfull haue and doo dailie caſt out diuels from the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. They haue ſpoken and doo ſpeake with new toongs. And though they drinke anie dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thing, it ſhall not hurt
<pb facs="tcp:6645:90"/> them. By which alſo they are procured to leaue their wicked minds, and diueliſh works, in the which they before lead their liues.</p>
               <p>They ſpeake thy holie word, and alſo ſet foorth thy veritie, leauing all lies and deceits. They doo ſuppreſſe the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſathan, plucking out the ſting of his taile, wherewith he was accuſtomed to wound them. And if at anie time they haue conſented to ſinne, and receiued his poiſon, this name of our ſauiour ſhall kéepe them from all hurts; bicauſe they made inuocation on his holie name, which dooth purge them cleane after their heartie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. For thou O Chriſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6645:90"/> wilt deliuer thine, though all worldlie meanrs faile. And though we be committed by tyrants vnto temporall death, yet through thée ſhall we van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh all our enimies: for the death of thy ſaints is deare and pretious in thy ſight: they néede not feare thoſe that haue power onelie to kill the bodie, but let vs feare thy mightie hand, which haſt power to ſlea both bodie &amp; ſoule. This world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie death is a waie to bring vs from much trouble, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of euerlaſting health, into the land of liuers.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe Lord, of thy iuſtice let the vniuſt and cruell enimies of the faithfull ſtand in dread of thy ſtretched
<pb facs="tcp:6645:91"/> out arme, wherewith in thine anger thou wilt ſtrike them. Of thine infinite goodnes thou ſuffereſt long, abiding their conuerſion; but after long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing thou ſtrikeſt verie ſore, throwing both bodie and ſoule into the pit of hell, hauing ſuch meaſure of puniſhment, as they gaine in this world. For as thy mercies is vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureable, ſo is thy iuſtice vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueable to thoſe that depart this world in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Make me, O Lord God, of the number of thoſe that be thy faithfull children; let me not wauer nor fall from my hope, but put on me the ſhield of faith, that I may ſtronglie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6645:91"/> fight againſt my ghoſtlie eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. Grant me to vanquiſh and ouercome him, that after triumphant victorie, I may liue and reigne with thée O Father, Sonne, and holie Ghoſt, thrée perſons, and one true and euerlaſting GOD; through the merits &amp; death of thy Sonne my Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, to the which moſt glorious Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, be giuen all honor, glorie, and praiſe, now and for euer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:92"/>
               <head>33. A praier to be ſaid at all times, wherein our frailties are confeſſed, and requeſt made to haue them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed art thou O GOD of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and bleſſed is thy holie name, which is moſt glorious for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Let the heauens bleſſe thée, and all thy creatures, thou art the Lord, ſtrong and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, gratious, ſlow to anger, and abounding in goodneſſe and truth, reſeruing mercie for thouſands, forgiuing ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, tranſgreſſions and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6645:92"/> ſinnes, making the wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, if they will repent with all their whole harts, and returne vnto thée.</p>
               <p>Thou viſiteſt the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children; vnto the third and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: for as thou art mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, euen ſo goeth iuſtice from thée. For thou ſetteſt ſo much ſtore by man, that thou haſt a regard ouer him, and dailie careſt for vs, O Lord God, and makeſt proofe and triall of him euerie houre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding thoſe with a fatherlie eie that ſerue thée in faith and truth.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt vſed correction vnto vs, but we gathered ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by no repentance; thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:6645:93"/> corrected vs, to the end we ſhould amend, but we refuſed thy fatherlie viſitation. For thoſe that are thine enimies, thou wilt declare thine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie iudgments againſt them; but thou wilt ſhew thy fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable kindneſſe towards thy children. For thou haſt ſaid; I wil puniſh them that ſerue me otherwiſe than I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, not ſparing the chéefe, that the people may feare and praiſe my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For to the wicked and carnall man thou appéereſt as a flaming fire, but vnto them that be drawne with thy holie ſpirit, thou art like a pleaſant ſaphir to be hold.</p>
               <p>Holineſſe perteineth vnto
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6645:93"/> thée O Lord GOD, and thou O GOD art moſt holie, and nothing vnholie may appéere before thée. Therefore whoſoeuer commeth vnto thée, muſt be waſhed from all ſinne and corruption. And ſéeing thou gouerneſt all things by thy prouidence, thou wilt put a difference betwéene the godlie and vngodlie. Wherefore we humblie beſéech thée O Lord GOD, lighten our hearts with thy holie ſpirit, that we maie féele thy fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, as thoſe that be thine elect doo. The right hand of thy maieſtie is glorious in power.</p>
               <p>Grant vs, O God, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie to depend vpon thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:94"/> with patience, from daie to daie, with full truſt in thy promiſes for our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. For though we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke thée iuſtlie to anger, O God; yet wilt thou neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake vs. Thou art our Lord almightie, Iehouah is thy name, which declareſt that thou art conſtant, &amp; wilt performe thy promiſe.</p>
               <p>Grant vs grace therefore, that we may worſhip thée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, in the place which thou haſt appointed vs: for thou O Lord requireſt puritie. We cannot be thine, except our ſinnes be purged with the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, by whoſe grace we may learne to deteſt all ſinne. Which grant vs all
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6645:94"/> to doo, O Father, for Chriſtes ſake, whoſe figure we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, on him we laie all our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes, who is able to beare the burthen of them for vs all. We preſent him to thée O Father, whom we know both can and will make vs cleane and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect before thée, whoſe mercies we dailie praiſe, with thée O father, and the holie Ghoſt, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="prayer">
               <head>34. An humblie confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſinnes before God, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a petition to haue the ſame remitted.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord heare my harty repentance, for I am ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and gréeued
<pb facs="tcp:6645:95"/> with the burthen of my ſins; the remembrance of them is intollerable. Wherefore looke downe vpon me with thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable eies of pittie, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me which lie here proſtrat before the ſight of thy maieſtie: for I confeſſe that I am wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en old in ſin and wickedneſſe, wherin I firſt was conceiued, but now my moſt hartie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is to be borne anew, and to be graffed in my Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>For thus my faith dooth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade me, that none can come too late vnto thée, who forga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the théefe all his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at his laſt houre, when he aſked mercie of thée. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other more examples I
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6645:95"/> find in my moſt holie word, how mercifull thou haſt béene alwaies to thoſe thy ſeruants, that ſought the ſame of thée. And ſhall I then deſpaire, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring dailie thy voice crie out vnto me, ſaieng; Come all ye that are heauie loden, and I will eaſe you. Knocke, and it is heard; aſke, and it is giuen.</p>
               <p>Who can yet thinke that he ſhall miſſe of mercie, if he craue it in faith; ſéeing thou art ſo true and iuſt in all thy promiſes? Thy creatures faile in their words and works, but thou kéepeſt thy promiſe and fidelitie, and thy word indureth vnremooueable for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. O thou God almightie, vnto whom all things are kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:96"/> ſhew on me thy mercie, euen in the ſight of the children of men, that they may knowe and ſée how gratious and mercifull thou art vnto thoſe, that giue ouer themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the hands of thy almightie Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Thou art the helper of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and fréendles, and there is none that may be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto thée that art ſo rich in mercie, and louing kindneſſe, that diddeſt not ſpare thine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie begotten Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, to giue him a ſlaine ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for my ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the whole world; but alſo haſt promiſed, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer dooth come vnto thée in his name, with full aſſurance
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6645:96"/> in his bloud, death, and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall not onelie receiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of all their ſinnes and iniquities that euer they haue committed, but alſo inherit the crowne of euerlaſting glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which thou wilt giue vnto all thoſe that be thine elect in Chriſt. Of which number, through thy grace, I account my ſelfe for one, making me moſt aſſured thereof, bicauſe thou haſt promiſed the ſame.</p>
               <p>Which dooth imbolden me at this preſent, to craue thy moſt mercifull aid, and aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thy holie ſpirit, to ſtrengthen me in faith, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme me in hope, to ſtabliſh me in charitie, that I may be knowen by thy cogniſance
<pb facs="tcp:6645:97"/> and badge, to be thy child and faithfull ſeruant; that I may vſe the talent which thou haſt giuen me, to thine honor and glorie, and the health of my ſoule.</p>
               <p>That when it ſhall pleaſe thée to take a reckoning, how I haue ſpent the gifts of grace, which thou haſt lent me, I may yéeld a iuſt account, with much aduantage, ſo that I may be worthie to heare thy voiee, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng vnto me; Come thou true &amp; good ſeruant, thou haſt béene faithfull in a little, I will make thée ruler ouer much; enter thou into thy maiſters ioie.</p>
               <p>O bleſſed and happie are they that ſhall be ſo placed of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6645:97"/> thée; they haue fought a good fight, and thorough Ieſus Chriſt haue ouercome the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, and prince of this world. Therefore ſhall they liue and reigne with the ſame Chriſt, their grand capteine; bicauſe they tooke him for their guide, in all their dooings, and fought manfullie vnder his banner. Thy poore ſoldier I am, Lord, and fight dailie. Lord helpe me for thy mercies ſake, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all mine enimies.</p>
               <p>Giue me, O Lord, a waking mind, an vnderſtanding hart, and renue in me a right ſpirit, which may lead me vnto thée, who art the waie, the truth and the life, whoſe mercies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for euer, whoſe truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth
<pb facs="tcp:6645:98"/> from generation to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Glorie be to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who ſo mercifullie crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs; and to the ſonne, who louinglie redéemed vs; and to the holie Ghoſt, who ſanctifieth vs, and maketh vs bleſſed, thrée perſons and one GOD, whoſe name be praiſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="prayer">
               <head>35. A thankeſgiuing vnto God for the redemption of the world, wherein is ſhewed from what graces he fell, and how he was reſtored.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt holie father of heauen, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie liuing God, of power ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6645:98"/> of wiſdome incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: to thée be honour, and glorie, and thanks, for thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble works, in the creation of mankind, and alſo for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption out of captiuitie, and thraldome of the diuell, by the paſſion of thy moſt deare beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. For thou madeſt <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt man, and gaueſt him frée will to obeie thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; from the which he fell by the intiſement of the diuell, and by his owne ſtubbornes, whereby he ſpoiled himſelfe and his after commers, of thoſe godlie gifts, which thou of thy mercie haddeſt beſtowed vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, thou of thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:99"/> goodneſſe diddeſt not vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie leaue him, but gaueſt him faith to beléeue thy promiſes made vnto him, and to vs all, in Ieſus Chriſt, with grace and obedience to kéepe thy lawe. By faith we beléeue in thée, by charitie we worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our neighbour, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as thou haſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. No man liueth without ſinne, but happie and bleſſed are they to whom thou giueſt thy grace, not to abide and ſléepe in ſin, but by penitence to come to a godlie conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Lord giue vs faith, and a willing heart to follow thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie word, ſo that we may exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our ſelues in it all the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6645:99"/> daies of our life. Make vs, O Lord, like vnto the wiſe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, that were prouided of oile in their lampes, againſt the comming of the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome. Then wilt thou know vs to be thy faithfull children by election, and open the gate to vs, that we may enter in, to our comforts. Which grant vs Lord for thy bleſſed ſonnes ſake, who to ſaue vs ſuffered bitter paſſion, whoſe mercies be praiſed for his goodnes, with thée O father, and the holie ghoſt, in the world of worlds, now and for euer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:100"/>
               <head>36. An other praier of praiſe and thankeſgiuing to the ſame purpoſe aforeſaid.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne thankes, moſt gratious &amp; heauenlie father, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold gifts which thou of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercie and goodnes haſt giuen him? Firſt for his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creation, wherein he excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all other earthlie crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; &amp; then for his redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through the bitter paſſion and reſurrection of thy moſt louing ſonne. For the which I, as one of thy poore creatures,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6645:100"/> moſt humblie giue thée thanks. For had not our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption enſued our creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it had béene much better for vs that we had neuer béene made.</p>
               <p>Thy loue aboue all other was moſt feruent, when thou diddeſt not ſpare to giue thine onelie begotten ſonne for vs, waſhing awaie all our filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the blood of that méeke lambe, thine onelie naturall ſonne, who being GOD, was made man, to the intent that we, who naturallie are the ſonnes of men, by him (through grace) might be made the ſonnes of God.</p>
               <p>And not being contented with this kindneſſe, thou alſo
<pb facs="tcp:6645:101"/> Lord, conſidering our weake and fraile nature, readie to ſinne, dooeſt with thy grace, guide vs and gouerne vs, as the ſhéepheard dooth his ſhéepe, ſuffering vs not to want anie thing, defending thy poore flocke from the rauening woolues, that would elſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure vs. Thy bleſſed ſonne hath put vs to féed in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, gréene, and beautifull paſture of his holie church, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vs to reſt in the vnitie thereof, by a liuelie faith and hope in him.</p>
               <p>Which church is verie plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, abounding with all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meate of the word of God, which nouriſheth and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life to the ſoule, as bread
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6645:101"/> and other food féedes the bodie. With this food thou diddeſt féed the prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> when thou diddeſt cauſe him to eate a booke, wherewith his bowels were filled, and it ſéemed in his mouth ſwéeter than honie.</p>
               <p>In this paſture runneth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a freſh and pleaſant riuer of running water of godlie doctrine, wherewith we often doo refreſh our ſoules. In this alſo is a water of ſpirituall waſhing, by baptiſme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we were woonderfullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed in our youth. For our ſoules being made foule, through the diuell and ſinne, by baptiſme are repaired and made beautifull, according to the firſt creation, that is, to
<pb facs="tcp:6645:102"/> thy likeneſſe and image: and by this water we are repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with thy holie ſpirit.</p>
               <p>This water ſaw the prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> long ago, guſhing foorth of the right ſide of the temple, and grew to a great riuer, that no man could wade ouer; to which water whoſoeuer we come, was made whole. Euen ſo, in the water of our baptiſme, we were borne againe, in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of godlie doctrine we are nouriſhed, and without theſe we are but dead in ſinne and wickedneſſe, and at the end ſhall go to euerlaſting death: but theſe waters are to vs a well ſpringing vp vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. And if at anie
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6645:102"/> time by our frailiie we fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne; yet is thy mercifull ſonne readie to receiue vs to his grace, and quicken our ſoules; if we be ſorowfull and penitent.</p>
               <p>By which grace he maketh vs alſo to knowe how to loue him, and not to eſtéeme the pleaſures of this world, but to haue our eies onelie fixed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. So that with thine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> we account all things but loſſe, that we may winne Chriſt, and be found in him, not hauing our owne righteouſneſſe, but that which ſpringeth of the faith which is in Ieſus Chriſt. Whoſe grace if we haue, though we walke in the vallic and ſhadow of
<pb facs="tcp:6645:103"/> death, yet we feare none euill; for thou art with vs.</p>
               <p>This life is a ſhadow of death, after which we truſt by faith to dwell with thée. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, whileſt we are here, thou art with vs, and thy ſonne hath alſo promiſed to be with vs vnto the end of the world; his rod of diſcipline and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection dooth chaſten vs, when we ſwarue at anie time out of the right waie: by which we iudge that he dooth loue vs; for whoſoeuer he be that he loueth, him he dooth chaſten. Chriſts ſtrong ſhéepheards ſtaffe dooth ſtaie vs, when we are weake, as a ſicke man is by his ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>In Chriſt thy ſonne is the fulnes of grace, from whom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilleth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6645:103"/> all goodneſſe that we haue; through his holie ſpirit is our cup filled full of pure li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor: it cauſeth vs, for ioie of heauenlie contemplation, to forget all the troubles and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of the world, the dregs of worldlie pleaſures, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections. For as thy mercie hath gone before vs, plentifullie giuing vs aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of thy great graces: ſo we truſt, and doubt not, but it will followe vs all the daies of our liues, and kéepe vs that we fall not from faith.</p>
               <p>Thou Lord muſt helpe our houſe, or elſe we labour in vaine; thou muſt be our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and end, and then we be ſure to dwell in the houſe of
<pb facs="tcp:6645:104"/> the Lord for euer. For we know ſurelie, that if our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie manſion, wherein we now dwell, were diſſolued, we haue a building ordeined of God, an habitation not made with hands, but eternallie in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where is perpetuall ioie and beatitude, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="prayer">
               <head>37. A breefe confeſſion, that we receiue all goodnes from God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſe vp O Lord God, and let thine enimies be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before thée, and let them that hate thée be brought to confuſion. Declare
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6645:104"/> O Lord thy might and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for thou art a conſuming fire, and a gelous God, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation. For thy gouernement is ſo iuſt, conſtant, and without change or repentance, that thy verie enimies ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to confeſſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>O God almightie, thou dooſt puniſh thine elect by meaſure, &amp; giueſt them grace to beare it; but to the reprobate, it is thy iuſt vengeance, to driue them headlong to all madneſſe. For thy omnipotencie hath all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in it ſelfe, to execute thy terrible iudgment againſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate ſinners: as thou art
<pb facs="tcp:6645:105"/> rich in mercy to comfort them which obeie thy word and loue thée.</p>
               <p>The faithfull, in all their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, doo knowe that all ſhall go well with them: for GOD will be mercifull and iuſt, and though they want for a time, yet thou wilt ſend them comfort in due ſeaſon. For thy Maieſtie is ſo great, that it fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth both heauen and earth, and there is no power ſo high that can let thée, when thou wilt deliuer thine. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked riſe vp ſuddenlie to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and periſh as quicklie; but the inheritance of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God continueth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. For thou O GOD wilt take vengance vpon the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6645:105"/> and meaſure them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their dealings.</p>
               <p>Thus thou O God canſt plucke backe the bridle of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and deliuer thine owne out of the lions mouth: for though the wicked ſwell ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much, yet we feare them not. They cannot vtterlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroie vs, for thou Lord haſt promiſed to abide with thy faithfull people, to the end of the world. Thy grace will not leaue vs, nor anie that loue thée and ſerue thée with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart. Thy fauour O God reſteth on thine, for thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake, that from him we might receiue thy bleſſings. For we deſerue nothing of our ſelues, but
<pb facs="tcp:6645:106"/> thy wrath and indignation.</p>
               <p>Wherefore grant vs, good Lord, firſt to ſéeke thy glorie, and aboue all things reigne thou ouer vs al, and let vs ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to thée perfect obedience, as thine angels doo, whom thou haſt commanded to take charge of thy children. For the which if the wicked deſpiſe them, thou of thy mercie wilt reuenge their cauſe: for thou wilt preſerue the faithful bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of thy vineyard; but the rotten ſtocks wilt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroie, according to their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. For there is none like vnto thée in heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, or in the earth beneath. Thou dooeſt bleſſe the labour of the poore, and conſumeſt the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6645:106"/> goods of them which are negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, bicauſe they boaſt and thinke they haue enough.</p>
               <p>The wicked wallow in their riches, yet are they but ſlaues to the godlie that are true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the gift of God. The cup which thou gaueſt to the wicked to drinke, is much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than that thou dooſt beſtow on thine own: them thou mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureſt by mercie, the other by iuſtice. And though thou ſuffer thy children to liue vnder the croſſe, leaſt they ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace wickedneſſe; yet thou wilt not ſuffer it to reſt vpon them, that it ſhould driue them from their hope: for all thy promiſes are true. Wherefore we are ſure of thy helpfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:107"/> ſéeing the earth and all creatures remaine in that eſtate, wherein thou haſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them; much more thy truth indureth conſtant and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable. Bleſſed be thou O God of truth, and bleſſed be the glorie of thy holie name, world without end, Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="prayer">
               <head>38. A praier wherein is ſhewed, that there is none omnipotent, but God alone.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord GOD al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, it is not in mans power or counſell to hinder that thou haſt determined ſhall come to paſſe: for as the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6645:107"/> inſenſible heauen is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to anie alteration and change, ſo ſhall the truth of thy promiſes be vnchangeable, ſith our infirmities cannot in any wiſe comprehend thée in thy maieſtie. There is none like thée, neither is there anie God beſides thée: thou killeſt, and giueſt life; thou woundeſt, and makeſt whole. Wherefore bleſſed are they that confeſſe thée, and obeie thy word: to them thou giueſt life and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</p>
               <p>The ioies that are ſtedfaſt and perdurable, are giuen of thy goodneſſe, to thoſe that are méeke and humble in ſpirit. Thou dooeſt grant to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of thy goodneſſe, both grace
<pb facs="tcp:6645:108"/> and glorie; ſo that no good thing ſhall be withholden from them that liue in thy feare: for thou caſteſt awaie none that will ſéeke thée in righteouſnes. And though thou ſuffer the world to hate thine elect, it is bicauſe thy children ſhould forſake the filthines of this world, and cleaue vnto thée. Wherefore grant vs, O Lord, that we may alwaies haue the eies of our faith fixed vpon thée: for whatſoeuer thou O GOD haſt promiſed, ſhall ſurelie be performed. For as it was thy frée mercie, O God, that did chooſe vs: ſo is it thy frée mercie that muſt ſaue vs. Thou dooſt call vs by thy rod, to conſider the ſhortnes of our
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6645:108"/> life: for our ſinnes haue abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our daies, which be not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhort, but miſerable, bicauſe we are ſo ſinfull, that we doo nothing but prouoke thée to wrath; ſo weake we are, ſo fraile, and vnable of our ſelues to doo that good is, inclining alwaies to things forbidden. There is nothing ſo ſecreatlie doone on earth, but thou O God dooſt ſée it, who dooeſt ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill both heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>Grant vs, O Lord, alwaies thy feare, which ſhall be a bridle to ſtaie vs from all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For as thou haſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all people, euen ſo dooeſt thou gouerne the hearts of all, ioining the ſaluation of thine with thine owne honour, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:6645:109"/> that they cannot periſh, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thy glorie ſhould be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. For thou art ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that a ſinner can no ſooner humble himſelfe, but thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueſt him to mercie, waiting as it were with patience, to call him to repentance.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we crie now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy maieſtie, from the depth of our hearts; moſt humblie beſéeching thée to put all our wickednes out of thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and giue vs grace to put our onelie truſt in thée, from whom we looke for our deliuerance, who ſhalt change our bodies, and make them like to the moſt glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt; to whom, with thée, &amp; the holie
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6645:109"/> Ghoſt, be giuen all praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glorie, now and for euer more, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="prayer">
               <head>39. A praier of lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein the ſinner lamenteth his miſerable eſtate, and crieth for mercie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, when I do earneſtlie behold mine owne ſtate, wherevnto I am brought through ſinne, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie being naked and bare of all goodnes, but alſo to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in the depth of all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie; I cannot but lament, moorne, and crie for helpe, as dooth a woman, whoſe time draweth néere to be deliuered
<pb facs="tcp:6645:110"/> of hir child; for ſhe can take no reſt, till ſhe be diſcharged of hir burthen.</p>
               <p>No more can I, Lord, as long as I féele my ſelfe loden with my heauie burthen of ſinne, the weight wherof draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me downe to the déepe bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of all miſerie; from whence I can by none be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, but onelie by thée, that art the guide and the eie to thoſe that are blind through ignorance, the ſuccor of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the comfort of the weake, the life of thoſe that are dead; ſo that they repent and turne vnto thée.</p>
               <p>It is not the long diſtance of vs from thy highneſſe, which kéepeth our praiers from thée;
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6645:110"/> thine eares are readie in the hearts of all that are willing to crie for the help of thy grace. Who ſo is made farre from thée, through ſinne, by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is made néere vnto thée. He that is in the bottom of the ſea of miſerie, if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to call for thy helpe, he ſhall not be ſuffered to ſinke. From all déepe dangers moſt mercifull God deliuer me.</p>
               <p>I crie and call pitiouſlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, which art onelie able to helpe me. Heare therefore, I moſt hartilie praie thée, my ſorowfull praier, and let my poore petition pearſe the eares of thy Godhed. And ſince thy ſonne Chriſt died for to releaſe vs of ſinne, let not my ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:6645:111"/> be a ſtaie, whereby my praiers ſhould not be heard, but wipe them cleane awaie, that they neuer more appéere. For I miſerable ſinner doo flie to the gentlenes of thy fauourable mercie, whoſe nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie is to haue pitie &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</p>
               <p>From thée floweth all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and grace, which was ſo great vnto vs, that it mooued thée to ſend thine onlie Sonne to die for our redemption; whereby thy iuſtice was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and thy mercie found that it ſought. O how feruent was this thy noble charitie to vs vile wretches! It tooke root &amp; beginning in thy mightie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie, &amp; from thence it was deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6645:111"/> to mankind; being an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that we thy chriſtian people ſhould, like louing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, beare one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I am moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie contented, to remit all iniuries doon to me; as it hath pleaſed thy goodnes to forgiue me much greater offenſes committed againſt thée. And whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe thée to ſcourge and puniſh me, I will gladlie receiue thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, for that I knowe it procéedeth of loue for my wealth and ſuretie; truſting that after my long abiding &amp; ſuffering in this life, I ſhall ſurelie obteine thy reward, by thy promiſe, that is; If we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:6645:112"/> with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo reigne with him.</p>
               <p>Such ſure hope haue I euer had in thée Lord, and by the ſame hope I truſt to haue thy fauour, and liue for euer. For bleſſed are they that truſt in thée, moſt mercifull Father; and curſed are they that truſt in man. Of thy grace and mercie onelie commeth all goodnes; thy mercie forgiueth onelie our ſinnes dailie and hourelie, &amp; the painfull death of thy ſonne Chriſt deliuereth vs from all the paines due for our ſinnes. Thou boughteſt vs not with gold and ſiluer, but with the pretious bloud of that lambe without ſpot, thy bleſſed Sonne, whoſe death had béene
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6645:112"/> ſufficient for thouſands of worlds.</p>
               <p>The greatnes of thy loue cauſed the plentifull paiment of the price of our redemption. The charitie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath burnt vp, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, by his death, all our iniquities. Wherefore the faithfull, being thus deliuered from all dangers, by thine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie goodneſſe, may now giue thanks vnto thy mightie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, reſting in hope to haue, after this life, euerlaſting ioie and felicitie; thorough Ieſus Chriſt our mercifull Lord and redéemer; to whom with thée O deare Father, &amp; the holie Ghoſt, be giuen all honor, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and praiſe, now and for
<pb facs="tcp:6645:113"/> euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="prayer">
               <head>40. A praier, wherein the fatherlie loue and preſeruation of God is ſet foorth, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt that we may continue faithfull and conſtant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Rant vs, O Lord that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie beléeue in thée; that being certified by thy iuſtice, taught by thy wiſedome, gouerned by thy power, we may ſtedfaſtlie perſeuere euen vnto the end, in hope of that ioie that is ſet before our eies, framing our liues continuallie in chriſtian exerciſes, that we may ſhew
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6645:113"/> our ſelues thankful to thée our God, with dutifulneſſe to our neighbour. For thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments appéere manifeſt in this world, againſt thoſe that ſuppreſſe thy word, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute thy ſeruants. For thou dooeſt diſappoint the lot and expectation of the wicked, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their ioie into ſorrowe, and the teares of the godlie into gladneſſe, dwelling in the harts of thy faithfull by thy holie ſpirit, who are called thy glorie, bicauſe thy image, and the token of thy grace ſhineth in them.</p>
               <p>Thou art a light to comfort thy people, and a fire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thine enimies. Thou art he, O Chriſt, that toucheſt the
<pb facs="tcp:6645:114"/> harts of all thy ſeruants, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieng their concupiſcence: but to the wicked thou art the ſauour of death. Wherefore the faithfull deſire of thée to be deliuered, that thou by them maiſt be glorified: for thou haſt promiſed to be true and iuſt vnto all that truſt in thée. Wherefore we will take thée for our defenſe againſt all our enimies, what danger ſoeuer we fall into.</p>
               <p>Thy word giueth life vnto man, cauſing him to ſée and trie the ſecrets of his darke heart. For thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe moſt liberall to thine, when they ſéeme to be moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, kéeping them vnder thy protection, that they may
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6645:114"/> be ſafe againſt all dangers, and frée from the cruelties of their enimies. For as to the elect all things turne to their profit; ſo to the reprobate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thoſe things that are good, turne to their damnation.</p>
               <p>As for me, I will neuer boaſt of mine owne vertues, O God; but confeſſe that thou of thy frée goodnes, haſt euer bin mercifull vnto me, and giuen me power againſt mine eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as to one of thine houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. Wherefore grant me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to make my praier vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, from the fountaine of my heart, that I offend thée not through hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>And though the wicked deale rigorouſlie with me, yet I
<pb facs="tcp:6645:115"/> beſéech thée let me find comfort from thée; for hitherto haſt thou ſtrengthened me againſt my outward and inward eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo that all the world ſhall confeſſe, that thou haſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfullie preſerued me, and performed thy promiſe. For thou dooeſt euer guide me with thy hand, that I can turne no waie but where thou appointeſt me. Thy prouidence doth ſo faſt hold me, that I cannot by anie meanes eſcape from thée. Thou haſt made me in all parts, and therfore muſt néeds know me. Wherefore, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy wonderfull worke in forming me, I cannot but praiſe thée, and feare thy migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power, who art the creator
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6645:115"/> of all things, the kéeper of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the louer of right, the hater of malice; beholding from the high throne of thy Maieſtie the children of men.</p>
               <p>Bow downe thine eare, O mercifull Father, I humblie beſéech thée, and heare me thy ſeruant, whom thou haſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto brought vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age, and deliuered me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this daie from the hands of the wicked, whoſe rage was furious, vntill thou brakeſt their force. I ſet my hope in thée O God, and life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, knowing that theſe earthlie things ſhall periſh, hauing a ſure hope, that both my ſoule and bodie ſhall inioy thy preſence, O God of my
<pb facs="tcp:6645:116"/> ſaluation, in the laſt reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then ſhall I féele thy mercies, and anſwere when thou calleſt me.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I ſet all my feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie and ioie in that I am v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited with thée O God, and ſhall inioie thy preſence; ſo that I reiect all other things ſaue that which furthereth me to attaine to thy heauenlie treaſures, which is ſure, and cannot be found in anie but in thée alone, whoſe praiſe ſhall indure for euer, world without end Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="prayer">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:6645:116"/>
               <head>41. A praier, wherein the ſinner praieth for grace, that he may make a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie end.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed Father of heauen, fountaine of all grace and goodnes, that art rich in mercie, and plentifull in giuing the ſame to all that doo faithfullie call vpon thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie name. O good God, thou hauing a ſonne no leſſe rich in power, wiſedome, knowledge, and mercy, than thou art thine owne ſelfe, diddeſt not ſpare to ſend him from thy heauenlie palace, downe to the earth, into the wombe of a virgine,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:117"/> for the ſaluation of mankind, to declare thine aboundant loue towards vs.</p>
               <p>Thou diddeſt for our ſakes make him poore, which before was rich; to the intent that we, which before were verie poore, ſhould by his pouertie be made rich; that he which before was all one with thée, in thy diuine ſubſtance, might now be made one with vs, that are members of the bodie, whereof he is the head. Hearken good Lord, giue eare vnto my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, let my petition aſcend vp before the ſight of thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. The comming of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull ſon did make me thine, but the vilenes of mine owne acts hath caſt me downe, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6645:117"/> made me verie miſerable. The greatnes of mine offenſes hath cauſed thée to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie thy face from me, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing thy grace, which was the cauſe of the good works I did.</p>
               <p>Thou canſt find no good thing in me, worthie of thy fauour; wherfore, Lord, behold the face of Chriſt thy deare Sonne, my mediator; for his ſake giue me that which of my ſelfe I am much vnworthie to obteine of thée. Looke on me with thy pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull eie, and in the time of my trouble incline thine eare and heare me. My old enimie dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſalteth me and vexeth me. Wherefore I will not ceaſe to call vpon thée dailie: but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:118"/> at the houre of my death Lord heare me &amp; defend me, at which time my cruel enimie will moſt buſilie inuade me. At that inſtant Lord looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me with the eie of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, now whileſt I am in this wretched world.</p>
               <p>I craue not of thée aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of earthlie goods, but as honeſt neceſſitie dooth require, but the aboundance of thy grace in this life. This haſt thou of thy méere liberalitie promiſed to grant, to all that in ſtedfaſt faith call vpon thée. This haſtie calling vpon thée dooeſt thou delight in, for thou art as redie to anſwer me, as I am to call vpon thée. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make ſpéed in hearing,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:6645:118"/> as I am bold to call vpon thée for I confeſſe O Lord I haue left thy holie word and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which is as bread vnto the ſoule, giuing nutriment and moiſture by faith and charitie, and haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the trée which thou forba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me.</p>
               <p>I haue, with our father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, followed the illuſions of the ſerpent, &amp; taſted of ſin; but thy bleſſed ſonne my ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt hath ſhed his bloud for vs, whereby we are reſtored vnto thy grace, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and fauour, through the ſacrament of baptiſme, if we hartilie repent. He quickneth vs, which before were dead in ſinne; he ſlaieth, and can raiſe
<pb facs="tcp:6645:119"/> againe; he ſtriketh and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: as he did <hi>Paule</hi> in his perſecution.</p>
               <p>How much therefore are we bound to his grace, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie deſeruing on our parts, willinglie offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the death for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: and to thy maieſtie alſo, who didſt not ſpare thine onelie begotten ſonne, but of thy pure pittie, ſentedſt him downe to ſuffer the moſt vile death of the croſſe for our ſakes.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I am much aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to lift vp my eies to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen towards thy highneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo vnkind to thée againe ſo manie waies. I haue loued the works of darkenes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6645:119"/> I fled from the light of the bright ſunne of iuſtice: for which cauſe doo I ſigh, ſorrowe, and bewaile my wretchednes, in the bitterneſſe of ſuch thoughts for feare of thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger towards me; knowing that at the time of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the dreadfull generall iudgement, the ſtorme of thine indignation ſhall go forth, and fall downe vpon the heads of the vngodlie.</p>
               <p>Thou lifteſt me vp of a great hight, in that thou thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me like vnto thine image, touching my reaſonable ſoule, and haſt giuen me power, by thy grace, to inherit euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ioies of heauen, both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule, if I liued here
<pb facs="tcp:6645:120"/> after thy rommandements. What greater gift canſt thou giue me, Lord, than to haue the fruition of thée? But alas I beare ſo heauie and erthlie fraile bodie, ioined to my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoule, that my heart and mind is drawne downe from the conſideration of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and from well dooing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all kind of vices.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, Lord, grant me, that in the ſhadow of this life, I may haue grace to ſée light, and to know thée, thy waies, and thy holie word, which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth light and vnderſtanding vnto babes: for after this life, there is no place nor time left of repentance. And ſince my time is here but ſhort, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6645:120"/> thy grace towards me, that I may liue in thy feare all the daies of my life, and end my life in thy fauour, who dooſt indure for euer, and thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance through all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, world without end, Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="prayer">
               <head>42. A praier againſt the offenſes of this world.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hart ſhall praiſe thée O GOD, for my ſoule is in loue with thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, for the which I deſpiſe all earthlie things, in reſpect of of thée the euerlaſting GOD, without meaſure, who féedeth all things. Thou art the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb facs="tcp:6645:121"/> of the ſoule, and the true ioie of the heart. Wherefore Lord continue thy graces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, and helpe our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſities: for we are far vnworthie of thy great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, which thou beſtoweſt vpon vs and all people, who appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the earth to bring foorth to mans vſe. Thou art a moſt nouriſhing father, prouiding for all creatures their dailie food; for none is able to do anie thing, but as thou appointeſt them, ſith they are but inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to doo thy worke, though intentions be diuers.</p>
               <p>Thou O God art the ſender of peace and warre, proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and aduerſitie, puniſhing whole nations for their ſinnes.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6645:121"/> How can we then ſo fooliſhlie perſuade our ſelues, that we ſhall eſcape vnpuniſhed for our offenſes? Séeing thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and ſéeſt all things, who haſt in all ages plagued all ſuch as maliciouſlie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſlie depart from thy truth. For who ſo forſaketh thée O God, ſhall be puniſhed, and made wearie of his ſinnes, wherein he delighteth. As for me, I hate them, O Lord, that preſumptuouſlie dare attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto themſelues, that they can guide their owne harts; ſéeing it lieth in thy om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie to giue the will, and further the worke. For there is none able to ſpeake a word, except thou giue it him;
<pb facs="tcp:6645:122"/> neither is anie able to thinke a good thought, without thée: much leſſe may anie doo the thing that good is, without the aſſiſtance of thy holie ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Wherefore regenerate me, O Lord God, by the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and reſtore me to thine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, giuing me grace, and an aſſured faith, to thinke &amp; doo that which is righteous in thy ſight. For I deſire to liue but onelie to pleaſe thée, as thy ſeruant <hi>Moſes</hi> did, who was brought vp with the daughter of <hi>Pharao,</hi> and taken as hir ſonne; where he might haue liued ſtill in much wealth, if he would. But when he was great through faith, he refuſed to be called hir ſonne, &amp; choſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6645:122"/> rather to ſuffer aduerſitie with the people of God, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioie the pleaſure of ſinne for a while; and all for that he had reſpect to the reward to come in thy heauenlie houſe.</p>
               <p>Which grant me to aſpire vnto, for thy mercie ſake, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer vexation or trouble my bodie bide. For what ſhould all the world gaine me, if I loſe my ſoule? Better I were in this world to féed vpon the bread of teares, and to waſh my cup with moorning, than to liue in all proſperitie, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in worldlie wealth, and forget thée my God, as the rich glutton did. For aſſuredlie it is thy plague, when the rich man hath not a liberall hart to
<pb facs="tcp:6645:123"/> vſe his riches, to thine honour and glorie. For there is no power ſo high or mightie, but thou O God canſt viſit him with thy rod; neither is there anie mountaine or hill ſo ſtrong or mightie, that it can preſerue the wicked from thy wrath, O moſt mightie, when thou wilt ſtrike; for thine office is to take vengeance on the wicked, and to reward them according to their wickednes and deſeruing. Bleſſe me, O GOD, and make me of that number, which regard not the pleaſures of this world, with the temporall commodities thereof: but make me ſtrong againſt my ſpirituall enimie, that I may be thy well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6645:123"/> child and ſeruant: for I haue no other refuge but thée O Lord, in whom my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is at reſt. Thou art named mercifull, gratious, and long ſuffering: Lord ſhew thy ſelfe ſo vnto me thy poore creature, who is moſt weake and fraile of all other.</p>
               <p>Lord I haue confeſſed all mine offenſes and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto thy Maieſtie: and now I depend wholie on thée, reſting ſtill on thy moſt holie word; beſéeching thée to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my poore ſoule, which ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and groneth vnto thée, with gréefes that cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, vntill thou haue mercie vpon me. Which grant me for thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:6645:124"/> our Lord and ſauiour, Amen, So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="prayer">
               <head>43. A praier for the good estate of the church and congregation of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſe O LORD GOD, and haue mercie vpon thy church and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full congregation. Giue vs that be of the houſhold of faith, ioie and conſolation. Thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt euer ſhew mercie vnto thy ſeruants; for euer ſince the fall of angels, vnto the end of the world, thy mercie hath euer béene, and ſhall be aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhewed to all mankind:
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:6645:124"/> but chéefelie it was ſhewed when thy ſonne was ſent into this world, to ſuffer death, whereby the gate of heauen was opened, which before was ſhut, that no man might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. This time was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of grace, and was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinlie appointed, when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time was come, which was before ſinne, by the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting wiſdome of thy deitie, whereby thou dooeſt all things in moſt perfect order. This time of grace, we truſt, ſhall continue for euer, to thoſe that are penitent.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we praie thée without ceaſing, to haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon thy church: for we faithfullie build vpon a ſure
<pb facs="tcp:6645:125"/> rocke, thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt is our foundation. Wherefore moſt louing father, turne thée vnto the praiers of vs that are poore &amp; deſtitute of any helpe; but onelie of thy helpe, through thy mercie. Deſpiſe not, we humblie beſéech thée, our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire. Behold our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with thy fatherlie eie, wherewith thou didſt looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the oblation of <hi>Abel,</hi> and receiue it thankfullie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with alſo thou beheldeſt the the praier of the Iſraelties, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in bitter bondage in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and deliueredſt them: with thoſe ſame mercifull eies vouchſafe to looke vpon vs, and our praiers, whereby the noble fame and praiſe of thy
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:6645:125"/> mercie ſhall be written for thoſe that come after, which ſhall be borne in faith by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and may praiſe thée. For thoſe that be thy children, ſhall haue a power aboue nature, &amp; in their age ſhall they bring foorth moſt ſwéet and pleaſant fruit.</p>
               <p>Thou wilt euer declare thy ſelfe the preſeruer of the church in deſtroieng thine enimies, as thou diddeſt in thy red ſea. Thou O God art mercifull, and wilt not forſake vs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroie vs: nor forget the appointment of our Fathers, which thou ſwareſt vnto them. And forſomuch as thou O God haſt appointed that thy church in this world ſhal be vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:6645:126"/> croſſe, both bicauſe we ſhould learne, not to put our truſt in anie worldlie thing, and alſo féele thy comfort when all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helpe faileth. Therfore we humblie beſéech thée O Lord, gather thy church which is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed, and giue vs conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnder the manifold croſſes which we ſuffer, that we may with one conſent all togither praiſe thée for euer. For thou haſt promiſed, by the mouth of thy ſwéet ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that thy power, and thine aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhall be with hir vnto the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Strengthen vs therefore with thy grace and holy ſpirit, that we may ſowe the ſéed of good works in this world, that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6645:126"/> they may declare vs to be thy faithfull ſeruants, and that they may be acceptable fruit in thy ſight: for thou dooeſt trie our faith, and teacheſt vs to forget the world, and to depend on thée O father of al goodnes. Thy promiſe neuer faileth, thou gouerneſt, by thy holie ſpirit, as ſéemeth beſt to thy godlie wiſedome: for thou O God art rich in mercie and truth, which féedeſt all things, and none can iuſtlie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine. For as by thy preſence all things haue life; ſo if thou withdraw thy bleſſing, we all periſh.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt a little flocke, féed them with thy ſpirituall foode, and gouerne thy church, ſéeing
<pb facs="tcp:6645:127"/> thou haſt choſen them out of the world: ioine it vnto thy ſelfe, that thy faithfull may continue for euer. For thou art euerlaſting, thou haſt euer loued truth, thou art veritie it ſelfe, all thy promiſes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remooueable. Thou diddeſt promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie his ſéed, as the ſtars of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and as the ſands vpon the ſea ſide; which promiſe at the laſt he enioied: euen ſo did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou promiſe <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob.</hi> When <hi>Ezechias</hi> was ſicke vnto the death, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt promiſe him life fiftéene yéeres more, which thou didſt performe for thy names ſake.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo Lord kéepe thy promiſe with vs, that are thy
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6645:127"/> poore ſhéepe, ſo ſhall we praiſe thée, and thy Sonne our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, which is our good ſhéepeheard; who ſuffered death for his flocks ſake, to make them triumph ouer their enimies. And as he roſe againe for our iuſtification, ſo grant that we may riſe in newnes of life, and aſpire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame place whither our ſauiour is gone before; whoſe name be praiſed, with thée O déere father, and the holie Ghoſt, now and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:128"/>
               <head>44. A praier, wherein is ſhewed, that the wiſedome of God is to be praiſed; as alſo how he trieth his ſeruants is declared.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou, O moſt mightie God art the creator &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of all things, whoſe power is euerlaſting, which ſhal neuer be put down; whoſe kingdome indureth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt for euer, and thy going out hath béene from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Great art thou, high &amp; vnmeaſureable; thou onelie knowſt the waies of wiſdome none other is there that can find hir paths, but thou the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6645:128"/> mightie God, which haſt found hir out with thy foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; &amp; by the ſame thy godlie wiſedome haſt created all things, according to thy noble will and pleaſure. This thine omnipotent power, Lord, I thy ſinfull ſeruant and ſubiect doo honour, and thy excéeding wiſedome I haue in great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. By the one thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt all things, and by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou kneweſt what thou wouldeſt make, long before they were made; in both theſe haſt thou declared thy ſelfe to be the liuing God.</p>
               <p>And although our acts, which be paſt, preſent, and to come, be all open before thine eies, and our thoughts manifeſt in
<pb facs="tcp:6645:129"/> the ſight of thy diuine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; yet dooeſt thou dailie ſearch and prooue thine elect people, ſometimes by aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſometimes by proſperitie, to cauſe vs thereby to be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to other. After this ſort diddeſt thou prooue <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the oblation of his ſonne, to the intent his obedience might be an example to all that ſhould come after him. Thus alſo diddeſt thou prooue thy ſeruant <hi>Iob,</hi> and he was found both faithfull, conſtant, and iuſt. Thou knoweſt what men be, before thou trieſt them. But after the triall, thou heareſt them &amp; their praiers, and alloweſt their good actes and intentions: by ſuch proofe,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6645:129"/> Lord, haſt thou tried me both within and without.</p>
               <p>And though through frailtie I haue erred, wandering from thée; yet at length haue I béene found to returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to thée, that art the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect waie, and to beléeue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie in thée, as in my verie God, to truſt wholie in thée, &amp; to loue thée as my mercifull father: and all through the gift of thy grace, not of mine owne ſtrength or will. For what were I ſillie wretch, if I were deſtitute of thy helpe? I doo conſider thy goodnes, and thy godlie prouidence, by which thou waſt the cauſe of my firſt being; and ſtill am I much bound vnto thy Maieſtie, for
<pb facs="tcp:6645:130"/> the great loue thou bareſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. Firſt for my creation, and alſo for thy meruellous protection, aſſiſtance, inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, redemption, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, which the eie of my ſoule dooth right well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I moſt humblie praie thée Lord, to regard what ſhall redound to thy glorie: for thine honour is more aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in ſauing one poore miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and ſinfull creature, through thy mercie, than in the damnation of a thouſand, by the rigour of thy iuſtice. For in hell none can praiſe thée, but curſſe, waile, moorne and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their miſerable eſtate. Now, O my GOD, I moſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6645:130"/> hartilie beſéech thée, to giue me grace to flie the companie of all ſuch as ſpeake vntrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of thée, and of thy holie will and word; &amp; alſo of them that exalt themſelues preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſlie, leaſt being conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in their wickedneſſe, I might fall from that right way, in the which it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy gratious goodnes to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me: for whoſoeuer is fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar with the proud, ſhal be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with pride.</p>
               <p>He that dooth euill, is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of death; ſo are all thoſe that communicate with him that hath pleaſure in euill. As for ſuch as decline from thée, I will abhorre: thoſe that doo me anie wrong, I cléerelie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue
<pb facs="tcp:6645:131"/> and forget whatſoeuer they doo vnto me; yea I doo praie vnto thée my moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father, euen from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my hart, to forgiue them. But thoſe, Lord, that maliciouſlie reſiſt thée, and thy holie word, I hate them, euen as though they were mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies. Neuertheleſſe, I doo praie thée for amendment of their liues, and ſaluation of their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Conſider Lord the frailtie of our nature, none can ſtand in the right waie, but ſhall ſlide and fall, vnleſſe thou giue him the ſtaffe of thy grace, to ſtaie himſelfe thereby. As for me, I haue wandered from thée, as a ſhéepe that is ſtraied
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6645:131"/> from the flocke: but thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hath found me out again, and brought me vnto the fold. Lead me therfore, out of mine owne wicked waie, into thie bleſſed waie of truth, through the merits of thy déer beloued Sonne Chriſt, who is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true perfect path to all bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, by whoſe helpe I may ſo direct my ſteppes, in the waie of this life, that I may kéepe the waie vnto life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:132"/>
               <head>45. A praier wherin is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed how ſtranglie preſerued, and how bleſſed they are, that truſt in God: the mercie of God alſo toward ſinners is declared.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord almightie, father of mercie, &amp; God of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which in the treaſure of ſhine infinit mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, diſpoſeſt all things, not onlie among vs thy poore cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures vpon earth, which is bountifullie repleniſhed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; but alſo among thy holy angels, and bleſſed ſpirits in heauen, who are all preſerued by thy grace. Lord God, whoſe nature and propertie is to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6645:132"/> haue mercie vpon all thoſe that loue thée, and in faith call on thée; thou ſaieſt by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſaie,</hi> that the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſhall remooue, and the hilles ſhall fall downe, but thy louing kindneſſe ſhall not mooue from thoſe that truſt in thée.</p>
               <p>Thou Lord, of thy mercie, ſauedſt <hi>Noa</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the generall floud; and <hi>Abraham</hi> in his voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; <hi>Lot,</hi> from ſinking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſinfull <hi>Sodomites; Ioſeph,</hi> from the danger of his wicked ladie and miſtres; the Iſraelites, from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of <hi>Pharao; Daniel,</hi> from the lions; <hi>Ionas,</hi> from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being thrée daies &amp; thrée nights in the whales bellie; the
<pb facs="tcp:6645:133"/> thrée yoong men, from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that were put into the flaming fornace; with manie thouſands more, whom of thy naturall accuſtomed mercie and goodneſſe, thou dooeſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and euer wilt doo, all thoſe that it pleaſeth thée to drawe vnto thée, thorough grace.</p>
               <p>I moſt miſerable and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner doo now call vpon thée for mercie and grace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging my ſelfe grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſlie to haue offended the eies of thy deitie, ſo manie waies, that I am not worthie to beare the name of a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; the burthen of mine offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is ſo great. Wherefore diſcharge me of them, Lord,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6645:133"/> according to thine infinit mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. For ſmall ſinnes, thy ſmall mercie ſufficeth; but my great ſinnes require thy great mercie. And as my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes are manie in number, ſo is there of thy mercies a great multitude: yea they cannot be numbred. But of one thing I am ſure, that it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in mans power ſo much to offend, as it is in thy mercifull power to forgiue. My woonds cannot be ſo great and noiſome, but thy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are moſt pretious and healthſome: wherefore heale thou me, and I ſhall be whole from my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>The children of Iſraell might not come into thy
<pb facs="tcp:6645:134"/> ſight, being once defiled with anie vncleanneſſe, till they were ſanctified; and the prieſts alſo durſt not come to thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, till they were waſhed, for feare leaſt they ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: how much more néed I then to deſire thée Lord to waſh my vncleane ſoule? For my ſoule hath néed of manie dews of thy grace, and manie ſecret drawings to thée with ſpirituall violence, or euer it can be made cleane. The lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Naaman</hi> of <hi>Syria</hi> could not be clenſed, till he had wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed himſelfe ſeauen times in the riuer of <hi>Iordan:</hi> how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie waters haue I néed to be waſhed with, or I be purged from my vncleanneſſe? But
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6645:134"/> thy mercie, O Lord, is as great as thy ſelfe. Thy grace maketh a ſtonie heart to be a fleſhie heart; in a ſturdie ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, it bréedeth an humble ſpirit; of a fierſe lion, it maketh a méeke lambe. Whie ſhould I then deſpaire of thy goodnes, conſidering that thy iuſtice willeth me to truſt in thée?</p>
               <p>Thy promiſe is to haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on all thoſe that be peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for their offenſes, ſo that thou wilt no more remember them. This promiſe no doubt, ſhall ſtand faſt and ſure, when both heauen and earth ſhall paſſe awaie. Wherefore I offer now to thy maieſty a hart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, being ſorie for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes by it conceiued, with a
<pb facs="tcp:6645:135"/> bodie ſubiect to thée with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and ſorowfull for all the ſinnes by it committed. I acknowledge my faults, and my ſinnes is euer before me; I puniſh my ſelfe with contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, bicauſe thou Lord ſhouldſt giue me grace and remiſſion. I haue it euer in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and ſet it vp in my ſight, bicauſe thou ſhouldſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it, and put it out of thy ſight. Conſider Lord (I praie thée) the fraile metall whereof I am made, receiue me thy poore creature into thy fauour: for before thée I accuſe my ſelfe, to the intent thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhew mercie, as thou haſt promiſed, who haſt euer béene found iuſt in all thy ſaiengs.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:6645:135"/>
               <p>I haue long ſtraied from thée, yet now am returned to thée, with all my whole heart. Make me therefore vpright. and ſo to aſpire to heauenlie things, that neither aduerſitie, nor worldlie pleaſure plucke it downeward. Caſt awaie my ſinnes behind thée, but caſt not me from thy mercifull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as thou diddeſt king <hi>Saule</hi> for diſobedience. For if I looſe thy gratious preſence, I am then ſure thou wilt alſo take from me thy holie ſpirit, as thou diddeſt from <hi>Saule.</hi> O how gratious and ſwéet is thy ſpirit in all things, it paſſeth all other ſwéetenes, it leadeth thoſe that loue thée, into the land of righteouſnes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:136"/>
               <p>This thy holie ſpirit I deſire may remaine ſtill with me, to teach me all veritie, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme me in goodnes, to make interceſſion for me vnto thée in all my neceſſities and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Giue me therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the comfort of thy helpe, and ſtabliſh me with thy prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſpirit. For thou onelie art mightie, faithfull, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and neuer faileſt them that call vpon thée in faith and truth. Wherefore I offer vnto thée the ſacrifice of praiſe and thankeſgiuing, for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and benefits, putting my whole truſt in thée, who haſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer failed me; for which cauſe I am bound to praiſe thée, now and for euermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="prayer">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:6645:136"/>
               <head>46. A praier of the maieſtie of God, and of his bountifull liberalitie towards mankind.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, thou art my GOD, and my King, my hope and my comfort, who haſt by ſo great proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence created and ordained all thy creatures, that the beautie &amp; excellencie of them declare thy mightie magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, to vs all which are thy reaſonable creatures. The power of thy maieſtie to vs knowne before, is by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of them made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, cauſing vs to praiſe and
<pb facs="tcp:6645:137"/> magnifie thée with all our powers. We acknowledge thy power, thy wiſedome, thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour alſo, and thy great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, wherewith thou art garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Thou art the euerlaſting light, and thy wiſedome is the brightneſſe thereof, which ſhall neuer be quenched. Thou art compaſſed about with bright angels, and with thy ſaints ſhining in cleareneſſe, whoſe inheritance is to enioie light.</p>
               <p>As for vs thy poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on earth, great cauſe haue we to praiſe thée world without end; bicauſe thou haſt ſo mercifullie declared thy great goodnes to mankind, in this world, to his moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that could be deuiſed, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6645:137"/> vnto vs all things to doo vs ſeruice. All beaſts thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſubiect for his vſe; which to nouriſh and to féed, thou cauſeſt the ground naturallie to bring foorth graſſe, and all kind of hearbes, repleniſhing the earth with all kind of fruit, to the comfort of mans heart.</p>
               <p>But aboue all things, Lord, féed vs with thy holie word, whereby our ſoules are made ſtrong and comforted. For in a miſerable caſe doo they liue, from whom thou takeſt awaie thy holie word, which is the true bread, which came downe from heauen: which whoſoeuer eateth of, ſhall liue for euer. Lord neuer take the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie
<pb facs="tcp:6645:138"/> from vs againe, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore féed vs with this bread. Thy word maketh our enimies afraid, they haue no further power to hurt thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, than thou permitteſt them. Wherefore, although the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſwell neuer ſo high, yet we feare them not; they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade thy church, and manie of the elect members of the ſame, but they ſhall neuer haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to deſtroie them. For thou Lord haſt promiſed to abide with thy faithfull, vnto the end of the world; thy grace will not leaue them that loue and ſerue thée.</p>
               <p>Send vs, good Lord, this grace, that we may feruentlie imbrace the ſpirituall food of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:6645:138"/> our ſoules, that it may cauſe vs to forget our wanton and idle liues, that we haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lead, and now beginne to frame a new, ſpirituall, godlie life, building the houſe of our ſoules on the ſure rocke, which is thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him as a ſure habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For it is he, Lord, that thou haſt annointed aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be our mediatour and mercie ſeat, who is ſo gentle, mercifull, and louing, that he is moſt readie to receiue vs, whenſoeuer we come vnto him. O glorious God, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent art thou? How noble and manifeſt be thy works, paſſing farre the capacitie of all thy creatures to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6645:139"/>
               <p>But thou full wiſelie haſt wrought all things, by the ſame wiſedome that hath bin with thée before anie thing was created, and before all times, by the which thou haſt numbred the ſands of the ſea, the drops of raine, the daies of time. By it haſt thou meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the height of heauen, the breadth of the earth, and the déepeneſſe of the ſea. This wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is thy verie ſonne, our Lord and Sauiour, the ſecond perſon in Trinitie, he is the power, in whom are hid all the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge. By him haſt thou wrought the worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and deliuered vs
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:6645:139"/> from eternall damnation.</p>
               <p>And although thou be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times angrie with vs for our wickednes; yet neuertheleſſe, if we call vpon thée in thy ſons name, thou wilt ſhew vs mercie: for it is thy nature and his to be mercifull. Lord kéepe our enimie farre from vs, let him not deuoure thoſe, for whoſe redemption and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thou vouchſafedſt to ſend thy moſt entirelie beloued ſon, to ſuffer death and paſſion. Bring them alſo (we humblie beſéech thée) into the true faith of thy holie church, that they may knowe thée, and him whom thou haſt ſent for the ſaluation of the world; that there may be on both ſorts one
<pb facs="tcp:6645:140"/> ſhéepheard, and one flocke. Send vs all, moſt mercifull father, thy gratious fauor, and open thy liberall hand, and fill vs all with thy goodnes, hide not thy face from vs for our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes.</p>
               <p>O ſend forth, good Lord, thy ſwéet breath vpon vs, make vs new againe, that we may leaue our old naughtines, and become new creatures. We acknowledge our ſelues to be duſt and aſhes, ſend therefore thine holie ſpirit to renew our ſoules, making it conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thine image, according as thou diddeſt firſt create it; which through ſinne we haue made verie fowle and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Then ſhall we giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:6645:140"/> vnto thy maieſtie, which indureth for euer, and thy kingdome from one generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to another, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="prayer">
               <head>47. A praier, wherein is ſhewed how bleſſed they are that feare the Lord.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord Lord, thou art a great God, mightie in power whom no man may ouercome. Let all thy creatures praiſe thée, for thou ſpakeſt the word, and they were made; thou ſenteſt thy ſpirit, and they were created, and there is none that may withſtand thy voice. The
<pb facs="tcp:6645:141"/> mountaines ſhall remooue from the foundations, and the waters ſhall melt like wax; but they that feare thée, ſhall be great with thée in althings. For thou dooeſt abhorre the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the vngodlie, but the praier of the righteous is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto thée: and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer followeth righteouſnes, him thou dooeſt loue.</p>
               <p>The feare of thée O Lord God, is a well of life, and the right waie to auoid the ſnares of death: for thou preſerueſt the welfare of the godlie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeſt them that walke inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centlie, and kéepeſt them in the right path, preſeruing ſtill the waie of thy ſaints, and neuer ſuffering their ſoules
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:6645:141"/> to féele hunger, but giuing them long life. As for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie, thou putteſt him from his deſires, ſhortening his yeares with gréefe.</p>
               <p>Lord grant me therefore to put my truſt in thée, with all my hart, that I neuer leane vnto mine owne vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; but in all my waies to haue reſpect vnto thée: ſo wilt thou order my goings. For it is thou O Lord, that giueſt wiſedome, &amp; out of thy mouth commeth knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. O God my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thou art he that haſt brought me vp, and lead me from my youth; therefore of thy mercie haue regard vnto me, and kéepe me ſtedfaſt in
<pb facs="tcp:6645:142"/> the feare of thée, in mine age, vntill I depart in peace, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy word. For mine eies doo dailie ſée thy ſaluation which thou haſt prepared for all thy people, which is thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>He is my mercifull media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, aduocate, and interceſſor, by whom I hope to haue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all my ſinnes: in him I liue, mooue, and haue my being; and after I am diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of this my corruptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, I beléeue, through his mercie, to riſe againe an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible bodie: for that I knowe my redéemer liueth, by whom I ſhall liue, and ſhall ſée him face to face, not with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eies, but with the ſame
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:6645:142"/> eies which I doo now, O God my ſauiour, lift vp with a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and repentant heart, for my moſt gréeuous ſinnes and iniquities, vnto the ſeat of thy maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Beſéeching thée, O my moſt ſwéet Lord Ieſus, to waſh me cleane, with thy moſt pretious blood, and make me one with thée, as thou and thy heauenlie father art one; and as thou ouercameſt, ſo grant me to ouercome all the temptations of the diuell, that I may be a piller in the temple of my God, and ſit with thée on thy ſeat, as thou haſt promiſed to all that ouercome the world, and die in the faith of thée. Thou art the waie, the truth,
<pb facs="tcp:6645:143"/> and the life. No creature commeth to the father, but by thée; and none can truſt in thée, except the father drawe him.</p>
               <p>O déere father, which art the good huſbandman, graft me in the true vine thy ſon. O Lord Ieſu Chriſt, nouriſh me a true branch in thée, that I may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide euerlaſtinglie, and bring forth much fruit. O holy ghoſt, water me with the dew of thy grace, that I may be gréene, and growe in the loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of my father and redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. O thou, which art the finger of Gods hand, touch my hart, and vnloſe the ſame from all blindneſſe and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I may heare the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:6645:143"/> voice of Gods heauenlie word, and bring foorth much fruit, vntill I be come vnto my full perfection, that I may be worthie to be placed among thy choſen and elect people: through the pretious death and blood ſhedding of Ieſus Chriſt, my onelie Lord and ſauiour; to whom, with thée, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be all honour and glorie, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="prayer">
               <head>48. A praier, wherein is ſhewed, that God dwelleth in the harts of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though his ſeat be in heauen.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He mightie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy diuine maieſtie, O Lord of Lords, and God
<pb facs="tcp:6645:144"/> of all gods, with the plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aboundance of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe daily declared vnto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, inforceth me to conſider mine owne weakenes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie, in yeelding to thée anie recompenſe. Thou Lord art omnipotent, and madeſt al things of naught: I am thy ſimple creature, made with thy hand, and without thy help I am able to doo no good thing. Thou art the GOD eternall, beſides whom there is no god; I am a woorme of the vile earth, not worthie to beare the name of a chriſtian, for that through mine own ſin, I haue defaced the beautie of the principall part of man, which is my ſoule, made to thy
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:6645:144"/> godlie image.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, ſince thou art the reformer of all our harts, and the inſpiror of all grace and goodneſſe, I moſt humblie beſéech thée, to correct by thy power, that which through my frailtie is amiſſe. Redres by thy pitie that which I haue mard through my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; make me able to yéeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, that which thou requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of me, acknowledging mine owne vnworthines; and to render vnto thée noble prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and louing thanks for thy manifold gifts of grace, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou haſt, of thy méere libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, indued both my ſoule and bodie. Make me worthie to laud thée, which I cannot doo
<pb facs="tcp:6645:145"/> vnleſſe thou giue me grace, to wipe awaie all mine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For thy praiſes be not ſéemelie in the mouth of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Yea Lord, I praie thée in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame my hart with the loue of thée, ſo that from the bottome thereof, I may ſpeake them, and not to loue anie thing in this world but thée, &amp; for thée. Thou art the true God and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and there is none but thou O Lord. Out of thy mouth commeth the word of righteouſnes, which no man may turne. Wherefore, all other gods ſet I aſſide, to thée onelie will I ſing praiſes, and confeſſe thée onelie to be the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing GOD, which I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:6645:145"/> before the whole congregation of the faithfull.</p>
               <p>Thou knoweſt the inward intent of the heart, for in the hearts of the beléeuing is thy ſeate, and reſting place. The ſoules of the iuſt are the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, wherein thou dooeſt inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. To this temple, good Lord, will I turne my ſelfe, by pondering the ſtate of mine owne ſoule; for ſtrength where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I call moſt humblie vnto thée, moſt mercifull God, that I may be able to vanquiſh the illuſions of the ſubtill ſerpent.</p>
               <p>Performe in me, that which thou haſt promiſed; for all thy waies are mercie and truth. Thy mercie reacheth vnto the heauens, and thy faithfulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6645:146"/> vnto the clouds: &amp; thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſtands like the ſtrong mountaine. When thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is conſidered, all the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the earth muſt néeds confes, that great is thy might and thy glorie. Neuertheleſſe, although thou dwelleſt aboue the heauens, yet haſt thou a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing reſpect vnto the lowlie and méeke of ſpirit, and dooeſt behold them, as one looketh on his friend, if they truſt in thée.</p>
               <p>Thou draweſt néere vnto them that ſéeke thée, to heare their praiers; yea thou art their ſhéeld and protection, in all their neceſſities: as for the proud workers of iniquitie, thou ſéeſt them a far off, thou beholdeſt them with a fearſe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:6645:146"/> looke, to their confuſion, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroie and roote out their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall out of the euerlaſting beatitude. Who ſo therfore will haue thy maieſtie come néere vnto him, muſt plucke downe his mind, and become lowe in heart. For the méeke &amp; humble people be thoſe that ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioie the heuenlie countrie. And though they walke in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of trouble, yet ſhalt thou refreſh and quicken them.</p>
               <p>This world is a place ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for trouble, and not for reſt. Here we are appointed to trauell, in this place is no want of tribulation: but thou euer gratiouſlie comforteſt the faithfull, thou ſuffereſt them not to be ouercome in any tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation;
<pb facs="tcp:6645:147"/> for through thée they vanquiſh all their enimies. Wherefore, Lord, powre out thy mercies (I beſéech thée) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy flocke; deliuer vs from all our enimies, ſpirituall and temporall; let thy right hand ſaue vs, and lead vs through thy grace, into eternall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. As for riches, eaſe, honor, or any kind of temporall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which be thy gifts alſo, but of thy left hand, we no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eſtéeme.</p>
               <p>Manie times thou beſtoweſt theſe benefits vpon thine eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the other thou reſerueſt for thine elect, to receiue after manie tribulations. And the ſame, Lord, I humblie beſéech thée, to kéepe in ſtore for me,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:6645:147"/> thy poore ſeruant. Regard not the wickednes which I dailie commit, but looke vpon the merits of thy ſon Ieſus Chriſt, my God and my ſauiour: for it is he that hath paied my debt, and thou Lord haſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the acquitance: grant me to honour thée therefore, as I ought to doo, now and for euer, Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="prayer">
               <head>49. A praier, wherein is ſhewed, that God is alwaies our protection, if we truſt in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, thou art my God; I will praiſe thée and magnifie thy name, and thy
<pb facs="tcp:6645:148"/> word aboue all things. Thou bringeſt maruelous things to paſſe, according to thy will and pleaſure. Thou art the poore mans helpe, &amp; a ſtrength for the néedfull in the time of trouble, defending them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all weathers, and their ſhadowe in the time of heate. Likewiſe to the preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, thou art like a ſtrong whirle wind, that caſteth downe the boaſting of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie, bicauſe they know not thée to be the euerlaſting ſtrength: but the righteous Lord, haue a reſpect vnto the waie of thy iudgements, and thy name and remembrance reioiſeth their hearts. As for my ſoule, it thirſteth after thée,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:6645:148"/> both daie and night; and my mind haſteth fréelie vnto thée, bicauſe thou art ſo mercifull vnto all them that ſéeke thée in ſingleneſſe of heart: for thou wilt be found of them that thirſt after thée.</p>
               <p>Thou art the well of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant waters, whorewith who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is filled, they ſhall neuer be a thirſt: for thou O lambe of GOD, that dwelleſt in the middeſt of the throne, wilt lead thine vnto the founteine of liuing waters, and giue them euerlaſting reſt; bicauſe that in this world they made themſelues white in thy blood, bearing thy croſſes with wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minds, and confeſſed thée before men on earth. For this
<pb facs="tcp:6645:149"/> cauſe wilt thou acknowledge them before God thy father in heauen, where they ſhall praiſe thée and him, world without end. O God moſt holie, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that I am none of thoſe that haue deſerued halfe ſuch mercie at thy hands: but I hope, through the mercies and merits of thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt my Lord and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, to be made as perfect before thée, O heauenlie father, as if I had neuer ſinned.</p>
               <p>For thus I ſtedfaſtlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue; if I come vnto him, he will not refuſe me; and if I praie heartilie, deſiring his helpe, he will heare me, and cloath me with his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and take from me all the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:6645:149"/> ſinnes that euer I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, from my birth vntill this preſent houre, as he hath promiſed in his holie word. Come Lord Ieſus, for thou art true and iuſt in all thy waies, and waſh me with thy moſt pretious blood. Sanctifie me with thy bitter paſſion, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious death, and glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Reſtore me to thoſe ioies, that thine elect doo find in thée, &amp; powre thy holie ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my heart, that he may draw my mind continuallie vnto thée: for thou art the waie, the truth, and the life. Bleſſed are they that truſt in thée, and with a ſtedfaſt faith make thée their onelie ſtaie and refuge; they ſhall be ſure of all happineſſe in
<pb facs="tcp:6645:150"/> this world: and when it ſhall pleaſe thée to call them hence, they ſhall enioie with thée, the crowne of glorie, who haſt all power giuen thée, both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth: for the father iudgeth no man, but hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all vnto thée, who art the verie wiſedome of God.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, Lord Ieſu, make me bleſſed with thée, like as thou art bleſſed; for I commit my ſelfe, both bodie and ſoule, into thy mercifull hands, who haſt redéemed me, O thou God of truth. Thou O Lord, art worthie to receiue all glorie, and honour, and might: for thou haſt created all things, and for thy willes ſake they were and are created. O moſt
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:6645:150"/> noble creator of light, ſhine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hart, that it may cléerlie ſée the excellencie of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; and quicken my ſoule and ſpirit, that they may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie be ſtirred to honour and glorifie thée, as thou art worthie, which by thy grace I ſhall not ceaſe to do, with hart ſoule, mind, and ſtrength, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thy faithfull congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which of thy mercie, Lord preſerue and kéepe, that we may praiſe thée, one God in perſons thrée, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in vnitie, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:151"/>
            <p>1584</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Henrie Denham</figDesc>
               <head>H D</head>
               <q>OS HOMINI SVBLIME DEDIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by Henrie Denham, dwelling in Pater noſter Rowe, at the ſigne <hi>of the Starre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6645:151"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
